What a troublesome bunch you are.
（多々良） お前らは 本当に困った奴らだな
But if you really wanna know, we'll tell you.
だが どうしても知りたいなら 俺たちが話してやるから
Take a seat there and listen up.
（百秋坊） ほら そこに座って ちゃんと聞きなさい
A long time ago, but not really that long ago.
（多々良） 昔々... と言っても そんな昔じゃねえ
This is about a little while ago.
ほんの少し前の出来事よ
（百秋坊） 世界に バケモノの街 あまたあれど
There are many cities in the world of beasts.
ひときわ賑わう ここ渋天街の
As many as 100,000 beasts live in the remarkably busy Juutengai.
すり鉢状の谷に棲みつく
バケモノの数 約十万
The grandmaster who's been leading them for a long time,
それらを長年 束ねてきた
バケモノの宗師様が
引退して神様に転生すると
宣言なさった
announced that he'd retire and reincarnate as a god.
He didn't know what kind of god he wanted to become,
何の神になるか思案するが
もし決まれば
but he allowed a successor to be chosen.
新しい宗師を
選ぶことになるので
He told everyone to prepare for this.
皆これに備えよとの仰せだ
（多々良） 強さ 品格とも
一流ってえのが跡目の条件だ
Strength and dignity were obvious requirements.
そこで まっ先に
名が挙がったのが
A beast called Iouzen made a name for himself right away.
猪王山ってえバケモノよ
He's a great person who's calm, brave, and has lots of disciples.
冷静沈着 勇猛果敢
大勢の弟子を抱える偉丈夫よ
He's also the father of two children, Ichirouhiko and Jiroumaru.
一郎彦と二郎丸っていう
２人の息子の父親でもある
"He'll surely be the next grandmaster",
次の宗師は
あいつに違いねえと
is what everyone was saying.
皆 口々に噂したもんさ
But there was another candidate.
（百秋坊） だが あともう １ 人
候補に挙がるバケモノがいた
His name was Kumatetsu.
名を熊徹といってな
その名のとおり
熊のごとき容姿に
As his name suggests, he looked like a bear,
was swift like a monkey, possessed bottomless strength,
猿並みに駆け回る
底なしの体力で
and wielded his sword masterfully.
自慢の大太刀を
ぶんぶん振り回す
力だけなら猪王山をも凌ぐと
When it came to strength,
he was said to surpass even Iouzen.
もっぱらの評判だった
By the way, this guy was a bit troublesome.
（多々良） ところが こいつが
ちょっと厄介な奴でな
He was violent, selfish, disrespectful, didn't have a single disciple,
粗暴 傲岸不遜
手前勝手ときたもんだから
弟子の １ 人もいやしねえ
let alone any children.
（百秋坊） ましてや息子なんかが
いるわけもなかった
Bakemono no Ko
Let's go.
（警官 １ ） さあ 来て
（少女 １ ） 触んないで やめて
Don't touch me!
（警官２） 未成年だよね
（少女２） 違います
You're minors, right?
We aren't!
（警官 １ ） 家出でしょ ？
（少女 １ ） だから違うって
You ran away from home, didn't you?
Like I said, we didn't!
Oh, indeed.
（蓮） ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ...
ハァ ハァーッ
ハァ ハァ...
キュッ
A baby mouse?
ネズミの子？
それとも...
Still, you're so tiny.
ちっこいなあ
Just a sec.
待ってな
Here.
ほら
Eat it.
食え
キュキュ キュッ ...
Did you run away from somewhere, too?
お前もどっかから
逃げてきたのか？
キュッ ？
I'm all alone, too.
俺も独りぼっちだよ
All right, let's take this.
（引っ越し作業員）
おい そっち持って
はい
Okay.
こっちから先だ
This one goes there.
Dad, where are you?
（蓮の声） 父さん
今どこにいるの？
What are you doing?
何してるの？
どうして こんな時に
来てくれないの？
Why aren't you here at a time like this?
Ren, it's time to go.
（親戚の男）
蓮 そろそろ行くぞ
Um, what about this?
（引っ越し作業員）
あの... これどうしましょう ？
Ah, we'll take that ourselves.
（親戚の女） あ それは
こちらで運びます
Oh...
Ah, be careful.
Ren, I know you're lonely after suddenly losing your mum,
（親戚の男） 蓮 母さんが
突然いなくなって
寂しいかもしれんが
交通事故だから仕方がない
but it can't be helped, it was an accident.
The head family will take you in.
お前は本家が後見人になって
引き取る いいな
All right?
You're our family's only boy and precious successor.
（親戚の女） あなたは
うちの家系唯一の男の子で
大事な跡取り
We'll raise you, so there's nothing to worry about.
これから何不自由なく
育ててあげるから
Ren, answer if you understand!
（親戚の男） 蓮 ！
わかったら返事ぐらいしろ ！
Why didn't dad come?
父さんは なんで来ないの？
Forget about him.
（親戚の男） あいつのことは
もう忘れろ
なんで？ 父さんは父さんだ
Why?
He's my dad.
（親戚の女） 母さんとあの人が
離婚したの知ってるでしょ ？
Don't you already know that your mum divorced him?
親権も裁判所が
こっちって認めたの
Plus, the courts gave us full custody of you.
He's just an outsider now.
もう赤の他人なのよ
I'll just live by myself then.
（蓮） なら １ 人で生きていく
（親戚の男） フン
子供が何言ってる
Hmph, you're just a kid.
You obviously can't do that.
そんなこと
できるわけないだろ
I'll live by myself.
１ 人だって生きてやる
強くなって
お前らを見返してやる
I'll become strong and get you all back for this!
（親戚の男） なんて口きくんだ
蓮 お前は...
How can you talk like that?!
Ren, you're-
大嫌いだ ！
お前らも父さんも
I hate you!
You and dad... I hate all of you!
全部 大嫌いだ ！
Ren, wait! Ren!
（親戚の男） 蓮 ！ 待て 蓮 ！
I hate you...
大嫌いだ...
大嫌いだ
I hate you...
大嫌い 大嫌い
I hate you... I hate you...
大嫌い
I hate you!
大嫌いだ ！
（影） ダイキライ
I hate you.
ダイ ... キライ ...
I hate... you...
Chiko?
（蓮） チコ
I'm all right, thanks.
大丈夫 ありがと
（チコ） キュキュキュ
キューン...
キュ ？
Geez, what's with that?
（大男） ったく 何だってんだ
I just have to be stronger than Iouzen, right?
要は猪王山より
強きゃいいんだろ
品格？ 意味がわからねえ
Dignity? What does that even mean?
（小男） 宗師様もムチャ言うねえ
The grandmaster is asking for a bit too much there.
How long did it take for the previous one to run away?
前にお前んとこにいた奴は
どのぐらいで逃げ出した ？
A month...
（大男） １ ヵ月... １ 週間 ？
１ 日...
A week?
A day...
He was gone by noon!
（小男） 午前中だぜ 午前中 ！
I hate whiny people like that!
（大男） メソメソしてる奴は
嫌いなんだよ ！
（小男） 選り好みしてる場合か
こうなったら
Can you afford to be picky?
At this rate, you'd be better off taking a random human or broom as your disciple.
その辺の人間でもタワシでも
ひっつかまえて弟子にするんだな
（大男） ああ そうかい
わかったよ
Is that so?
Got it.
Hey, I was just joking! Don't take it seriously!
（小男） おい 冗談だよ
真に受けんなよ
Hey!
（大男） やいっ ！
I said, hey!
やいって言ってんだ ！
Are you alive or dead?
おめえ 生きてんのか
死んでんのか
（蓮） うるせえ
Shut up.
If you can talk, I guess that means you're alive.
（大男） 口がきけるってこたあ
生きてるな
Where's your mum?
おっかさんは どうした ？
Shut up.
（蓮） うるせえ
（大男） じゃ おとっつぁんは？
What about your dad?
（蓮） 黙れ
Shut up.
（大男） 答えろ ！
おとっつぁんは？
Answer me!
Where's your dad?
Shut up!
（蓮） 黙れ 黙れ
黙れ 黙れ
If you keep talking, I'll kill you!
それ以上 話しかけたら
ぶち殺すぞ ！
Who're you killing, brat?
（小男） 何が殺すだ ガキが
（大男） もっとよく面見せろ
Let me see your face.
A b...
A beast...
バケモノ
Not bad.
悪くねえ
That's enough, don't you think?
もういいだろ
You wanna come with me?
おめえ 俺と一緒に来るか？
Eh?
Huh?!
はあ ？ お お前
バカ言え 熊徹 ！
S-Stop saying stupid things, Kumatetsu!
What was that?
何だ？ さっきの...
A dream?
夢？
Hey you, did you run away from home?
ねえ 君
家出してきた ？
L-Let go!
は... 離せ ！
子供が夜中に出歩くの
よくないでしょ
Children shouldn't be out in the dead of the night.
離せよ ！
Let go of me!
（警官 １ ） 保護者の連絡先は？
（警官２） 迎えに来てもらうから
What's your guardian's phone number?
We'll have them pick you up.
No...
イヤだ
Let's go.
（警官 １ ） さあ 来て
Absolutely... not!
絶対に...
イヤだ ！
Wait!
（警官たち） 待ちなさい
こら 待て ！
Hey, wait!
Stop!
止まりなさい ！
Hey!
こら ！ おい ！
Where'd he go?
どこだ
どこ行ったんだ？
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ...
（警官 １ ） あっちか
Over there?
No, this way!
いや こっちだ
Is this really Shibuya?
ここ 本当に渋谷？
Huh?
あれ？
Huh?!
Ow...
いってー
（蓮） あっ あれ？
Huh?
あれ？ 今来たはずの道がない？
They way I just came from is gone!
The way out... Where's the way out?
出口... 出口は？
ハァ ハァ ハァ...
離せ ！
Let go!
What's this?
何だ こいつ？
人間の子供だ
It's a human child.
Why is it here?
なんで ここに ？
This is perfect, let's tear off his skin and sell it to the lute maker.
ちょうどいい
皮をはいで
三味線屋に売るか
カラカラに乾かして
削り節にするか
Maybe we should dry him out and shave off bits for bonito flakes.
それとも...
Or...
たっ 助けて ！
H-Help!
（百秋坊） やめろ バカ者
Stop it, you idiots!
Huh?
あん？
（百秋坊） 罪深いことを言うな
Don't say wicked things like that.
チッ 何だ えらそうに...
He's acting all high and mighty.
Don't let it bother you.
（百秋坊） なあに 気にするな
They just look and talk a bit rough, that's all.
あいつらは口と顔が
ちょっと乱暴なだけさ
There's nothing to be afraid of.
怖がることはない
I'm Hyakushuubou.
私は百秋坊
As you can see, I'm a monk.
見てのとおり修行の身だ
ここ 渋天街へは
You can't come to Juutengai unless you follow the exact route.
定められた順路を巡らねば
たどり着けん
神にすらなれる我らバケモノ と
なれぬ人間とでは
We beasts who can even become gods,
and you humans who can't, live in different worlds.
生きる世界が違うでな
Coming here by accident must have been scary.
偶然に迷い込んで
心細かったろう
さあ 私が元の世界に
送り届けてあげるから...
Come with me, I'll lead you back to your world.
（男） よう おめえ
本当に来たのかい？
Yo!
You actually came?
Ah!
（熊徹） へへっ
見込んだとおりだぜ
I knew you had something in you!
ますます気に入った ！
I'm starting to like you!
Come here!
おらっ
What are you doing?
何をする
He's a lost child, be gentle!
それは迷子の子供だ
優しく寄り添わんか
寄り添うだ？
Gentle?
All you monks do is spout off such nonsense.
坊主は甘々なことしか
言わねえな
乱暴に扱うなと
いうことだ
I'm telling you to not be rough!
What's wrong with being rough?!
乱暴で何が悪い ！
And he isn't lost.
迷子なんかじゃねえ
Starting now, he's my disciple!
こいつは今から
俺の弟子だ ハハッ
弟子？
Disciple?
I told you already.
言っただろ 忘れたのか
You forgot?
You're taking a human child as your disciple?!
人間の子供を弟子にするのか？
It doesn't matter whether it's a human or a broom!
（熊徹） 人間だろうが
タワシだろうが
知ったこっちゃねえ
弟子っつったら
弟子だ ！
A disciple is a disciple!
（多々良）
待て 待て 待て
Hold on!
俺はやめとけって
何度も言ったんだがね
Didn't I tell you multiple times not to do it?
多々良 訳を話せ
Tatara, explain what's going on.
The grandmaster told him he must
have a disciple if he wants to be the successor.
宗師様が
跡目を目指すなら
どうしても弟子を取れと
こいつに仰ってな
But unlike in Iouzen's case, no one wants to be his disciple.
だが猪王山なら
いざ知らず
こいつの弟子になんざ
誰もなりたがらねえ ヒヒッ
And just when we were sightseeing the pitiful humans,
で 哀れな人間を
見物に出かけた時に
このガキを見つけた と
we found this brat.
So you kidnapped him?!
それで さらってきたのか？
ついて来たのは
こいつだよ
He followed us all by himself.
That's no reason to get a stranger involved!
（百秋坊） だからといって
関係のない者を巻き込むな
Are you saying I can't set my sights on anyone I think's got potential?!
見所のある奴に目ぇかけちゃ
いけないってのかい
Huh?!
Hey!
おい ！
（百秋坊）
なんとムチャクチャな
He's so unreasonable.
そこまでして
跡目の座が欲しいのか
Does he want to be the successor that badly?
No, no.
いやいや あいつはただ
He only wants to win a fight against Iouzen.
猪王山とのケンカに
勝ちてえだけよ
何のこたあねえ
That's all.
確かに
Indeed, becoming the grandmaster and
reincarnating as a god doesn't seem to interest him.
宗師となり神様に出世するなど
さらさら興味ないだろう
Even if he became a god,
仮に あいつが転生しても
せいぜい九十九神が
いいところさ
he'd probably be a tsukumogami at best.
"god of tool"
Maybe a toilet god, or a broom god.
便所の神とか
タワシの神とかな
It's the human child I'm worried about.
気の毒なのは
あの人間の子供だ
Do you think it'll be okay to leave him with Kumatetsu?
熊徹と一緒にして
大丈夫だろうか？
さあね 俺ぁ知らね
Who knows.
Not my problem.
フゥーッ
What do you mean by disciple?
（蓮） 弟子って何なんだよ
It means I'll be providing for you from now on.
（熊徹） 俺がこれから
食わしてやろうって言ってんだ
It's not like I asked you to.
（蓮） 別に頼んでねえよ
You sleep there.
（熊徹） ここで寝ろ
ただし俺は
メソメソする奴は嫌えだ
However, I hate whiny people.
泣いたらすぐ放り出す
If you cry, I'll throw you out.
泣かねえよ
I won't cry.
そうこなくちゃな
That's the way!
That doesn't mean I've agreed to become your disciple.
だからって あんたの弟子に
なった覚えはないからな
Then why did you follow me?
（熊徹） じゃ なぜついて来た ？
Why...
なぜって...
Even if you don't answer, I can tell.
言わねえでもわかるぜ
行く所がねえことぐらい
You've got nowhere else to go.
（蓮） 同情してんのか？
Are you pitying me?
You idiot!
バカ野郞 ！
You can only say that after you've become an adult!
んなこたあ
一人前になってから ほざけ
You'll have to keep living alone anyway.
おめえは どのみち
１ 人で生きてくしかねえんだ
I don't know your name yet.
まだ名前聞いてなかったな
I'm not telling you.
言わない
Huh?
（蓮） 個人情報だから
It's personal information.
ああ ！ なら年は？
Fine! And your age?
Nine...
"Kyuu"
きゅう...
All right, from now on, you're Kyuuta!
"ninth boy"
じゃ おめえは今から
「九太」 だ
Why do you get to give me a name?
なんで あんたが
名前付けるんだよ
（熊徹） いいか 九太だからな
It's Kyuuta from now on, okay?
Well then, I'm going to sleep, Kyuuta.
さて 俺はもう寝るぜ 九太
（女性） 蓮
Ren.
I made your favourite ham omelette.
蓮の好きな
ハム入りオムレツ作ったよ
Eat it before it gets cold.
冷めないうちに食べよ
Okay.
ふわあああっ
フン 逃げたか
So he ran away.
I knew this would happen...
どうせそんなこったろうと
思ったぜ
ふわあああーっ
おおっと ！
He must have really disliked his new name!
いやがった いやがった
It's time for breakfast!
メシだ
Stop it!
（蓮） やめろー ！
Still angry?
（熊徹） まだ怒ってんのかよ
I was just messing around a little.
ちょっと ふざけただけだろ
機嫌直して食えよ
Cheer up and eat.
These are fresh eggs.
うみたて卵だ
生で食わねえと もったいねえ
Not eating them raw is a waste.
Or are you not hungry?
それとも腹減ってねえのか？
減ってるよ ！
I am!
なら食え ！
Then eat!
生の卵なんか ！
Raw eggs are...!
Huh?
They're gross, who'd eat them!
生臭くて食えるか
普通に食うだろ？
Everyone does!
Look, like this!
見てろ おらー
どうだ ！
See?
バカじゃね？
That's just stupid.
What was that?!
（熊徹） 何だと こら
（蓮） 汚え
I forbid my disciple to be a picky eater!
弟子は
好き嫌い禁止だ ！
I'm not your disciple!
俺は
あんたの弟子じゃねえ ！
Shut up and eat!
うるせえ 食え
イヤだね
I won't!
どうしても
食わねえつもりなら...
If you're hell-bent on not eating...
What are you gonna do?
どーすんだよ
口ん中に放り込んでやる ！
I'll stuff them in your mouth!
やめろ 熊徹 優しく扱え
Stop it, Kumatetsu.
Be kind.
わかったろ 熊徹
You get it now, don't you, Kumatetsu?
Just send that brat back home.
そんな小憎らしいガキ
とっとと突っ返してこい
Huh?
あれ？ どこ行った ？
Where'd he go?
あんたなんか大っ嫌いだ ！
I hate you!
待て こら 九太 ！
Wait right there!
Kyuuta!
Kyuuta?
九太？
おっととと
おい ！
Hey!
Who'd wanna become your disciple?!
誰がお前なんかの弟子になるか
Wait, you!
（熊徹） 待て この野郎 ！
おっとと...
おっととと
Where'd he go?!
どこ行った ？ ええい ！
The way out...
出口... 出口は？
Where's the way out?
Sorry to keep you waiting.
お待たせ
Nii-chan, you want some?
（二郎丸） 兄ちゃん 食べる？
I see.
そっか
じゃ オイラ １ 人で食べよ
I'll eat it all by myself then.
I guess I'll start with the mandarin.
まずはミカンから...
（蓮） ごくん
Nope, changed my mind.
（二郞丸） やっぱやめた
I'll eat the cherry first.
最初はサクランボにする
Look, Jiroumaru!
（一郞彦） 見ろ 二郞丸
父上だ
It's father!
えっ ？ 父ちゃん ！
Dad!
Ichirouhiko, Jiroumaru, has your training been going well?
（猪王山） 一郎彦 二郎丸
稽古に励んでいるか？
Yes!
（二郎丸・一郎彦） はい ！
父上 私にも
稽古をつけてください
Father, I'd love for you to train me as well.
もちろん すぐにでも
Of course, right away.
Master.
（弟子 １ ） 師匠
時間をつくるから
もう少し待っていてくれるか
I'll make some time, so can you wait a little longer?
えー また ？
Huh, again?
はい ！
Yes!
I'm sorry.
すまぬな
熊徹 ！
Kumatetsu!
おう 猪王山
Oh, Iouzen.
I heard you got yourself a disciple for the first time in a while.
貴様も久方ぶりに
弟子を取ったそうだな
ああ それがさっそく
どっか行っちまってよ
Yeah, but he ran off somewhere.
見かけなかったか？
こんなちっこいガキなんだが
Did you see him?
He's a brat about this small.
A child?
子供？ お前自身が
子供のようなのにか？
Even though you're quite the child yourself?
Tch, shut up.
チッ うるせえなあ
I'm saying this as the father of two children,
これは２人の子の父親としての
意見だが
何の経験もないお前には
とても保護者は務まらん
being a parent will be difficult for you because of your lack of experience.
ああ そうかい
Is that so?!
I'm the type that doesn't change his mind once he's decided on something.
俺はこうだといったん決めたら
それ以上 曲げねえ性分でね
それより九太だ
Anyway, Kyuuta's really fast...
まったく すばしっこくてよ
人間のガキっていうのは...
These human kids...
Human?
人間だと ？
おい 弟子というのは
人間の子供のことか？
Your disciple is a human child?!
（弟子２） 師匠 ！
Master!
It hurts!
いってえ 離せ ！
Let go!
A human?
人間 ？
Why is it in our world?
なぜ我らの世界に...
That's a human?
人間 ？ あれが？
Why's a human here?
なんで人間なんかがいるんだ？
Oh, Kyuuta!
おお 九太 ！
Hold on, Kumatetsu!
（猪王山） 待て 熊徹
悪いことは言わん
I won't make fun of you, just put him back where you found him.
あの子供を元の場所に
捨て置いてこい
何だよ 人間の １ 匹や２匹ぐれえ
What's the problem with a human or two?
None of you probably know the real reason...
お前や皆は
知らんかもしれぬが
なぜ我らバケモノ と人間が
棲む世界を異にしているか
why we beasts and humans live in separate worlds.
While humans are weak,
人間は ひ弱がゆえに
胸の奧に闇を宿らせるという
they can harbour darkness deep in their hearts.
What if the darkness gets to him and we can't control him?
もし闇につけ込まれ
手に負えなくなったら...
Darkness?
闇？ へっ
あいつの中に
I didn't see such a thing in him.
そんなものがいるようにゃ
見えなかったがね
Listen, this problem doesn't concern only you!
聞け ！ これは
お前 １ 人の問題ではないのだ
What happens to my disciple is my decision!
俺の弟子をどうするかは
俺が決めんだよ
I'm warning you, for the sake of everyone in Juutengai, stop it!
いいか 警告するぞ ！
渋天街の皆のためにも
やめろ ！
（バケモノたちの ざわめき）
For everyone's sake?
皆のため？
You think you've already become the new grandmaster, Iouzen?
もう新しい宗師にでも
なったつもりか 猪王山よ
なに ？
What?
Let's see if you can stop me by force.
なら力ずくで止めてみろよ
なんなら跡目の決着
今ここでつけたっていいんだぜ
We can even decide the next successor right here.
Iouzen and Kumatetsu are having a showdown!
（バケモノ １ ）
猪王山と熊徹の対決だ ！
（バケモノ ２） 待ってました ！
（バケモノ ３） 場所を空けろ
Finally!
Clear the area!
（バケモノ ４）
新しい宗師が決まるの？
The new grandmaster is going to be decided?
Gather around!
（バケモノ ５） もっと下がれ
（バケモノ ６） すっげー
This is great!
Calm down, Kumatetsu!
熊徹 落ち着け
Nice, go get him!
いいぞ やれやれ ！
俺 猪王山
I'm betting on Iouzen!
俺も猪王山
I'm betting on Iouzen, too!
Me, too!
それじゃ賭けになんねえだろ
We can't bet if everyone chooses the same guy!
Well, well..
（猪王山） やれやれ
（一郞彦） 父上
Father.
下がっていろ
Stand back.
（バケモノ ７）
何だ あの熊徹の熊度
What's with Kumatetsu's attitude?!
（バケモノ ８） 礼儀を知らんのか
Don't you have any manners?!
（バケモノ ９）
バカにしてんのか こら
Are you making a fool of us?!
（バケモノ１０） 猪王山を見習え ！
Learn from Iouzen!
（二郎丸） おい
（一郎彦） 作法に則れ
Hey!
Show some etiquette!
He doesn't have any etiquette in the first place.
あいつに作法なんて
あるかよ
あのバカ
That idiot has turned everyone against him.
この場の全員を敵に回しおって
Are they going to have a sword fight?
これから斬り合いになるの？
The grandmaster has prohibited the unsheathing of swords,
（弟子２） 刀を抜くのは
宗師様が禁止した
みんな 鍔と鞘をヒモで結んで
抜けないようになってる
Our swords have their hand-guards tied to the sheaths, so they can't be drawn.
へーっ そうなん...
Is that... so?!
Hey, wait!
ま 待て こら ！
Where'd  he go?!
どこ行った ？
何をやっとるんだ バカめ
What's that idiot doing...?
That's his way of provoking the enemy.
（多々良）
ありゃ あいつなりの挑発よ
Whoa, as expected of Iouzen!
（バケモノ１１） さすが猪王山 ！
He's gonna do the same thing?
今と同じことをやる？
He got him!
やった
Idiot!
バカめ
くっそおー
Damn!
Whoops...
（熊徹） おっとっとっと...
We're not done yet!
Father!
父上 ！
Don't worry.
案ずるな
Ready....
（バケモノたち） はっけよ～い ！
Go!
のこった ！
（熊徹） うりゃあああ...
（バケモノ１２） キャーッ
（バケモノ１３） よけろ ！
Out of the way!
Iouzen is being driven into a corner!
（バケモノ１４）
猪王山が追い込まれてる
（バケモノ１５）
勝負は決まってしまうのか？
Has the match been decided?!
Iouzen, don't give up!
猪王山 がんばれ ！
Iouzen!
（バケモノたち） 猪王山
猪王山 猪王山
猪王山 猪王山 猪王山...
No one...
（蓮の声） 誰も... 誰も
あいつを応援してない
No one is cheering for him.
He's... all alone.
あいつ 独りぼっちなんだ
Iouzen!
（バケモノたち） 猪王山
猪王山 猪王山
うぐっ ！
Damn!
くそっ ！
Had enough yet?
まだやる気か？
I won't stop until I've beat you!
おめえに勝つまでやるぜ ！
Give it a rest already.
もうやめとけ
What?
なんの...
We're not done yet!
（バケモノ１６） 猪王山 ！
Iouzen!
You can do it, Iouzen!
（バケモノ１７） 行け ！ ほら そこだ
があっ ！
Get him, Dad!
やっちゃえ 父ちゃん
ぐわっ ！
Kumatetsu!
熊徹
Don't you lose!
負けるな ！
Who was that?
（バケモノ１８） 誰だ？
（バケモノ１９）
熊徹を応援する奴がいるとは
There's someone who'd cheer for Kumatetsu?
（バケモノ２０） 誰？ 誰？
Who is it?
Don't you lose!
負けるな ！
Kyuu-
きゅう...
It's over!
キマった ！
That's enough.
（宗師） そこまで
あ... 宗師様
Grandmaster.
（宗師） 何をしておるか
試合には早い
What are you doing?
It's still too early for the match.
I haven't yet decided what kind of god I want to become.
わしはまだ何の神になるか
決めておらん
Grandmaster, please punish Kumatetsu for bringing in a human.
宗師様
人間を引き入れた熊徹を
罰してください
ふむ
しかし罰と言っても
You say "punish",
こやつは おぬしが
のしてしまったではないか
but you seem to have punished him plenty yourself.
誰が... 何と言おうと
I don't care what anyone says, Kyuuta is my disciple!
九太は俺の弟子だ
ほほう
覚悟はあるようじゃな
I see you're determined.
Are you going to make an exception for him?
例外を認めるのですか？
気の毒だが
熊徹に責任など取れない
It's unfortunate, but Kumatetsu can't take responsibility!
I'll take responsibility.
責任は わしが取る
I'm the one who insisted on Kumatetsu taking a disciple, after all.
弟子を取れと焚きつけたのは
この わしじゃからのう
But if he allows darkness into him...
ですが もし闇を宿したら ？
（宗師） 何も人のすべてが
It's not like all humans are consumed by darkness.
闇に のみ込まれるわけでも
あるまいて
But...!
しかし ！
Why are you always so easy on Kumatetsu?
どうして そう熊徹に
甘いのですか？
This conversation is over.
（宗師）
話は終わり じゃ 解散～
Disperse!
熊徹
Kumatetsu, be grateful the grandmaster has such a kind heart.
宗師様の寛大なお心に
感謝せよ
Damn!
くそっ ！ あああっ
You're strong, aren't you?
（蓮） あんた 強いな
Weren't you watching?
何見てたんだ おめえは
If I can really become strong by staying with you,
（蓮） もし あんたといて
本当に強くなるんなら
俺 あんたの弟子に
なってやってもいいぜ
then I don't mind becoming your disciple.
（熊徹） フン どうせ
また逃げ出すんだろ
You'll probably run away again.
これ まだ賞味期限あるよな？
These haven't expired yet, right?
オエーッ
D-Delicious...
う... うめえ
パクッ
オエーッ
All right, Kyuuta!
よし 九太
I'll train you thoroughly, prepare yourself!
しっかり鍛えてやるから
覚悟しとけ ！
オエーッ
アーッハハハハハハ...
It suits you, Kyuuta.
（百秋坊）
ほう よく似合うぞ 九太
Quiet!
うるせえ ！
フン 今からやるのを見てろ
Watch carefully.
Splendid, splendid!
見事 見事
Got it?
（熊徹） わかったか
わかったらやれ
If you got it, do it!
Do it...?
やれって...
Kyuuta, do your best.
九太 がんばれ
えいっ
やあっ
えいっ ああ...
やあっ やっ
やあっ
いってててて
Ow!
やあっ
Stop.
やめろ やめろ ！
Stop it!
Where should I make improvements?
ど... どこを直せばいい？
ほっ 直すだってよ
笑かすぜ
"Improvements", he says!
You're making me laugh!
It can't be helped, it's my first time!
し... 仕方ないだろ
初めてだし
"First time!"
初めて ！ 僕初めて ！
ハハハ...
"My first time!"
（熊徹） ええい 黙れ ！
Enough, shut up!
（百秋坊） ただ やれと言って
やれるものか
Simply saying "do it" isn't enough.
ちゃんとイチから説明してやれ
Explain properly from the beginning.
Explain?
（熊徹） 説明？
（百秋坊） それが師匠の務めだろ
Isn't that the master's duty?
All right then.
仕方ねえ まずはだな
First, hold your sword like oomph.
剣をグーッ と持つだろ
そんでビュッ といって
バーンだ
Then do whoosh and bam!
Okay?
えっ そ... それだけ ？
That's it?
Like I said,
いや だから
hold it like oomph, then do whoosh and woom!
グーッ と持って
ビュッ といって ドーン ！
Okay?
Oomph?
Like I said, oomph!
いや だからグーッ と
（九太） グーッ...
（熊徹） 違う 違う 違う
Oomph...
No, no, no!
It's uumph.
グイーッだ
Uumph!
（九太） グ グイーッ
（熊徹） 違う 違う 違う 違う
No, no, no, no!
It's wuumph!
グエーッだ
Wuumph!
（九太） グ グエーッ
（熊徹） 違う 違う 違う 違う 違う
No, no, no, no, no!
Gyuumph!
ギュエーッ
（九太） ギュエーッ
（熊徹） ギョ ーエーッ
Gyoomph!
G-Gyoomph!
（九太） ギョ ギョ ーエ...
（熊徹） 違う ！ 違う 違う 違う
No, no, no, no!
It's all wrong!
全然違う ！ ったく
勘の悪い奴だな もう
Man, you really catch on slowly!
やってられるか ！
No wonder I can't do it!
What?!
なに ？
How do you expect me to do it with that kind of teaching?!
そんな教え方で
できるわけないだろ
Stop complaining and just do it!
（熊徹） つべこべ言わずにやれ
（九太） イヤだ
No.
（熊徹） やれ ！
（九太） イヤだ
Do it!
No.
Damn...!
あー くそっ
九太は初心者だ
もっとかみ砕いてだな...
Kyuuta is a beginner, explain it simpler.
ああ わかったよ
Yeah, I got it!
I'll explain it even more detailed then!
じゃ懇切丁寧に言ってやる
Grasp the sword in your heart!
胸ん中で剣を握るんだよ
あるだろ 胸ん中の剣が ！
You have one in your heart, don't you?!
Huh? How could I have such a thing?
（九太）
は？ そんなもんあるか
The sword in your heart is important!
胸ん中の剣が重要なんだよ
It's right here!
ここんとこの ！ ここんとこの ！
Right here!
Do it if you understand!
わかったらやれ ！
Do it!
やれ ！
Where are you going?
どこに行く ？
What's up with him?
何だ あいつ
どなり散らすばかりで
All he does is yell...
熊徹 待て 熊徹
Kumatetsu!
Wait, Kumatetsu!
フン 何が胸の剣だ バーカ
How can there be a sword in my heart, idiot.
（多々良） おめえよ
もう里に帰んな
You should go back home.
Huh?
A disciple usually needs five to ten years of training.
弟子っつったら
５年や１０年の修行はザラだ
You won't make it if you take it so lightly.
そんな生っちょろい覚悟で
務まるかよ
If you're just looking for free food,
ただ食っていきてえだけなら
go bother someone else in the human world.
人間の世界で面倒みてもらえ
ここには
お前の居場所なんかねえ
This isn't the place for you.
If you understand, make yourself scarce!
わかったら自分から失せろ
Where's he?
あいつは？
Not sure.
さてね
He said he'd be gone for 2-3 days.
２～３ 日いないようなことを
言ってたが...
Can you tell me what a disciple is supposed to do?
教えて 弟子って何をやるのか
First would be cleaning, laundry, and cooking.
（百秋坊） まずは
掃除 洗濯 炊事
What's with the sudden change?
急にどうした ？
昨日のことか？
Is it about yesterday?
Not really.
（九太） 別に
ゲホッ ゲホゲホ...
Forget about it.
ほっとけ あいつは
すぐ頭に血が上るタチだが
He may get mad quickly,
but it's all forgotten by the next day.
翌日には すっかり忘れて
ケロッ としている
It's not something you should be worried about.
こっちが気に病むだけ損だ
Like I said, that's not it.
（九太） だから違うって
They'll get wrinkled like that, stretch them out a bit.
それじゃあ シワになる
もっと振りさばいて
Okay.
ふむ
I've never had a human customer before.
人間に物を売るのは
初めてだよ
そうですか
Is that so?
How long are you gonna be around?
いつまで いるんだい？
I don't know.
さあ
How unsocial.
何だい 無愛想だね
Geez, these humans...
ったく しょうがないね
人間ってのは
（女の子たち） わあーっ
Damn human!
人間 この野郎 ！
怪獣 この野郎 ！
Damn monster!
I heard my father talk about it.
父ちゃんが言ってたの
聞こえたんだ
Sooner or later, humans become uncontrollable.
人間は そのうち
手に負えなくなるって
I'll exterminate you while I still can!
オイラが今のうち
退治してやる
Stop it, Jiroumaru!
やめろ 二郞丸
Nii-chan.
兄ちゃん
How could someone so weak become a monster?
こんな ひ弱な奴が
怪獣になどなるものか
Next time my brother bullies you, call me.
今度 弟がひどいことしたら
僕にお言い
叱ってやるから
I'll scold him.
You're dead if you rat me out!
（二郎丸） 告げ口なんかしたら
承知しねえぞ
（一郞彦） もうよせ 二郞丸
Enough, Jiroumaru!
（二郎丸） オイラ 弱い奴を見ると
ムカッ腹が立つんだ
Seeing weak people makes me angry.
おい 兄ちゃんは強えぜ
Hey, my brother is really strong!
Like a hermit, he can move things without touching them!
仙人みたいに
触らずに物を浮かすんだ
Come on, show him, too!
ねえ あいつに見せてやってよ
No!
ダメだ 力は
見せびらかすためじゃない
Doesn't father always say that strength isn't for showing off, but for kindness?!
優しさのためにあると
いつも父上が言っているだろう
I may still be a child, but I'll train hard...
僕はまだ子供だけど
しっかり修行して
いつか父上のような
長い鼻と大きな牙の
and one day become a great swordsman
with a long nose and big tusks like father.
立派な剣士になるんだ
Me, too!
俺もなる
父ちゃんみたいに
かっこいい剣士になる ！
I'll become a cool swordsman like dad, too!
Let's go.
（一郎彦） 行くぞ
（二郎丸） うん
Yeah!
「こんな ひ弱な奴」 か
"Someone so weak", huh...
Damn!
くそっ ！
いやー
ん？ 何だ こりゃ
The hell?!
Who did this?!
誰だ ！ 勝手に片づけたのは？
It was your disciple.
お前の弟子だが
Don't do unnecessary things!
余計なことするな ！
Huh?
What's with those bruises?
何だ その傷は？
（熊徹） へっ 情けねえ
Pitiful.
Geez, aren't you ashamed of being beat up?
やられっぱなしで
恥ずかしくねえのかよ
あーあ ったく
確かに俺は弱いよ
情けないよ
Indeed, I'm pitiful and weak.
It's as you say.
言うとおりだよ
As long as you understand.
わかりゃいいんだ
じゃあ俺も
言わせてもらうけど
Then let me be blunt.
What about you?
あんたはどうなんだよ
Huh?
（九太） あいつは早起きだ
あんたは昼まで寝ている
He wakes up early, you sleep till noon.
He's busy, you have time to spare.
あいつは忙しい
あんたは暇だ
Even though you have time, you're not doing anything.
暇なくせに何にもしてねえ
Are you talking about Iouzen?
あいつって猪王山のことか？
Even though he's busy, he's polite.
（九太） あいつは
忙しいのに丁寧だ
Even though you have time, you're short-tempered.
あんたは暇なくせに
雑で いいかげんだ
何が言いてえ？
What are you trying to say?
I totally get why you couldn't defeat him!
（九太） あんたがあいつに
勝てない理由がよくわかったぜ
What was that?!
（熊徹） 何だと この野郞 ！
Say it again, I dare you!
こら もういっぺん
言ってみろ ！
I'll say it as many times as I have to!
何度だって言ってやるぜ
あんたなんか最低だ ！
You're the worst!
落ち着け ２人とも
Calm down, you two!
How dare you talk like that to your master?!
（熊徹） 何様だ てめえ
師匠に向かって
（九太） 師匠なら師匠らしくしろ
If you're a master, then act like one!
（熊徹） なに ？
What?!
The smallest things make you mad!
（九太） ちょっとしたことで
頭にくる
Hey!
（熊徹） おい
You give up quickly!
（九太） すぐに無理だと投げ出す
（熊徹） 意見しようなんざ
いい度胸じゃないか だがな
It's fine that you have the guts to express your opinion,
but a disciple should just shut up and listen!
弟子は黙って
言うこと聞いてりゃいいんだ ！
In your dreams!
イヤだね あんたの言うこと
聞いてたら
If I listen to you, I'll become stupid!
バカがうつるぜ
Stay still, you!
（熊徹） 黙れ この野郎 ！
Shut up, idiot!
（九太） うるせえ バーカ
許してやってくれ 九太
Forgive him, Kyuuta.
不器用すぎる男なんだ
大目に見てやってくれ
This is just how he is, please understand.
Ah, Kumatetsu, let's go outside!
（多々良） 熊徹 外行こうぜ
なあ 外行こう
Stop!
Outside!
Let go! Let go!
（熊徹） 離せ 離せ ！
くそっ くそっ くそっ
Damn, damn, damn!
I'm trying the best I can!
俺にしてみたら精一杯
やってやってんだよ
Yet what's up with that kid?!
なのに何なんだ あの野郞 ！
（多々良） もう懲りただろ？
さっさと放り出しちまいな
You've had enough, right?
Just kick him out already.
Besides, I don't have spare time!
大体 俺は暇じゃねえ
I chop wood, catch fish and pick tea to earn a living!
薪割りや左官や茶摘みの
バイ トで稼いでんだ
His share, too!
あいつのぶんまで余分にな ！
（多々良） もうやめちまえ
それがいい
Just stop, you've done enough.
なのに なんで
So how could he say those things?!
あんな言い方されなきゃ
なんねえんだ そう思うだろ？
Right?!
I couldn't agree more.
ごもっとも ！
前みたいな独り身が
いかに気楽かよくわかったろ
You were living alone before, so you should know.
Living alone is awesome!
いいぜ 独り身は
責任もねえし
めんどくさいこともねえし
No responsibilities, no annoyances!
You don't even have to have a full stomach!
本当のこと言われて
腹を立てることもねえし
Uh...!
Oops, shouldn't have said that one.
おっ 口が滑った
Practising till late at night is commendable, Kumatetsu.
（宗師） 夜遅くまで稽古とは
感心じゃぞ 熊徹
宗師 ！
Grandmaster!
Letting your disciple see how hard you work should serve as a good lesson.
自ら努力する姿を
弟子に見せて
学ばせるのもよいことじゃ
Uh, yeah, that's what I was thinking...
（熊徹） ウッ... は はい
そう思います
よろしい
褒美にこれを授ける
Very well.
These shall be your reward.
（熊徹） 何すか それは？
What are those?
紹介状じゃ
Letters of introduction.
Letters of introduction?
（熊徹） 紹介状？
Take your disciple and travel around the country.
（宗師） 弟子を連れて
諸国を巡る旅に出よ
これを持てば各地の宗師に
すぐにでも面会できる
You can meet the other grandmasters in no time with these.
で ですが
B-But...
（宗師） 名だたる賢者たちじゃ
These famous sages can give you clues about what real strength is.
真の強さを知る手がかりが
つかめるであろう
しかし...
But...
Well then, have a nice trip!
（宗師） では よい旅をな～
（多々良） あーあ
It was a good chance to ditch the brat.
ガキをほっぽり出す
いいチャンスだったのに
宗師様の言いつけじゃ
断れねえなあ
But since this comes from the grandmaster, you can't refuse.
Too slow!
（熊徹） 遅い ！
遅い ！
遅い 遅い 遅い ！
くっそー ！
Damn!
At least eat your food slowly...
メシぐらい
ゆっくり食えよ お前ら
Excuse us for asking.
（百秋坊） おそれ多くも
お尋ねいたします
What is strength?
強さとは何ぞや？
My arms aren't very strong,
（賢者 １ ） わしは
晼っぷしは強くないが
but look, I can create illusions.
ほい 幻は
作り出すことができる
Don't make light of it!
あなどるな
幻は時として
真実よりも まことなり
Illusions can sometimes be more real than reality itself.
これ すなわち...
That is...
すなわち ？
That is...?
（賢者１ ） 強さなり ホホホ...
...strength.
What is strength?
（百秋坊） 強さとは？
Why do you seek something like that?
（賢者２） そんなものを求めて
何になる？
I possess some telekinetic powers,
（賢者２） わしは念動力を
少々たしなむが
but no matter how strong I am, there are things I can't win against.
いくら強さを誇っても
勝てぬものがあってのう
That is...
それ すなわち...
That is...?
すなわち ？
Can I ask you for something?
（賢者２） おぬし すまんがのう
（九太） は？
Could you please massage my back?
その... 腰をもんでくれんかのう
腰痛に念動力は効かぬゆえ
あいててて...
Telekinesis doesn't work on back pain.
Ow, ow, ow...
Strength?
（賢者３） 強さ ？
You're asking the wrong person.
それをわしに問うのは筋違いじゃ
Whether it's rainy or windy,
（賢者３） わしは ただ
雨の日も風の日も
石のように
ここに座っておるだけ
I simply sit here like a stone.
Why?
なぜです？
時を忘れ 世を忘れ
自分自身をも忘れ
To forget time, the world and myself in order to transcend reality.
現実を超越するため
That is...
すなわち...
That is...?
すなわち ？
She turned into stone.
（百秋坊） 石になってしまわれた
フン
Strength?
（賢者４） 強さ ？
わしゃ達観などせん
I'm not one to philosophise.
I catch my prey faster than anyone else.
誰よりも早く
獲物を釣り上げ
あーん
The one who gets to taste everything in this world wins.
世のあらゆるものを
味わった者勝ちじゃい
スキあらば
むしゃぶりつくがよい
If you like something, don't hold back.
That is...
これ すなわち...
That is...?
すなわち ？
TL Note: This is a pun on "An opening!" using suki (to like),
which probably implies: "I do whatever I want!"
An opening!
スキあり ！
Don't worry, I don't eat guests.
安心せい 客は食わぬ
ふわあああー
See?
（熊徹） ほら 見ろ
たわごとを聞いてたら
自分を見失うだけだ
If you listen to that nonsense, you'll lose your way.
（多々良） 食われて
自分自身も失うところだったぜ
I was almost eaten alive!
Strength seems to have many meanings.
（九太） 強いって
いろんな意味があるんだな
They all said interesting things.
どの賢者の話も面白かった
（熊徹） はーん
If you liked it so much, why don't you just study quietly sitting at a desk?
じゃ机にちょこんと座って
お勉強でもしてろ
（九太） ああ その方が
よっぽど有意義だね
At least learning like that would be worthwhile!
少なくとも どっかの誰かみたいに
Unlike a certain someone's oomph and gyoomph!
ビューとかギョエーとか
言わないからな
（熊徹） 意味なんか
てめえで見つけるんだよ
You have to figure it out yourself!
（九太） 説明できないくせに
Just because you can't explain!
（熊徹） おめえの勘が悪いだけだろ
It's because you're a slow learner!
（九太） あんたの教え方が
悪いんだろ...
It's because you're bad at teaching!
What a slow-learning disciple!
When it comes to arguing, your stamina is endless...
（百秋坊） お前たち
いがみ合う体力だけは尽きないな
What was that?!
Give it a rest, I'm tired!
（多々良） 勘弁してくれよ
疲れてんだから
Can't sleep?
眠れないのか？
Do I lack talent?
俺 才能ないのかな
Are you worried about it?
気にしてるのか
He calls me a slow learner.
勘が悪いって
I don't agree with that.
私はそうは思わないな
Be it laundry or cleaning, at first you knew nothing about it,
洗濯も掃除も
最初は何も知らなかったのに
but with little teaching you got the hang of it quickly.
ちょっと教えたら
すぐにコツをつかんだ
Those who work sincerely learn fast.
素直で働き者で
物覚えも早い
But...
でも...
The problem lies with Kumatetsu.
（百秋坊） 問題があるのは
熊徹の方だ
Look at his techniques, they're a mess.
あいつの技を見ろ
メチャクチャだ
In other words, he created them.
つまり独創的だ なぜか？
But why?
He has no parents and no master.
あいつには親も師匠もいない
He became strong all by himself.
あいつは自分１ 人で強くなった
強くなってしまったんだ
He became stronger.
That is his talent and also his misfortune.
それが あいつの
才能であり不幸だ
If you never listen to anyone, you can't give proper advice.
誰の言うことも聞かない代わりに
誰かに適切なア ドバイスも
できない
I see.
そうだったんだ
しかし たまに 「うむ なるほど」
と思うことがある
But sometimes, he says "Oh, I see."
Do you get it?
何かわかるか？
"You have to figure it out yourself."
「意味は自分で見つけろ」
ってこと ？
Exactly, I believe that's his principle.
（百秋坊） そう
一理あると思ってな
I don't know a better way to teach.
（熊徹） どうやって教えていいか
わかんねえよ
To think the peerless Kumatetsu-sama...
（多々良） 天下無双の熊徹様が
あの憎たらしいガキに
そこまで こだわるとはね
would fuss over that cheeky brat so much.
そ そんなんじゃねえ
I-It's not like that!
まっ 憎たらしさじゃ
ガキの頃のおめえも負けてねえ
Well, you weren't any better when you were little.
Even though you were weak, you sure were noisy.
弱えくせに口だけ達者でな
Only because I didn't have a master!
（熊徹） あん時ゃロクな師匠が
いなかっただけだ
The grandmaster was the only one who'd put up with you.
（多々良） 宗師様以外 誰も
おめえを相手にしなかった
Because you were troublesome and would never listen,
you'd get beat up over the smallest things.
言うことを聞かない
面倒な奴だって
すぐにサジ投げられてた
Damn, just remembering them pisses me off!
くそっ ！
思い出しても腹の立つ
最低な連中だ
Indeed.
（多々良） まったくだ
今のおめえ そっくり
He's just like you right now.
Well, I'd prefer it if he were gone as soon as possible.
まっ 俺はあんなガキ
さっさといなくなれと
思っちゃいるが
But if you're going to continue being his master,
もし このまま
師匠を続ける気なら
ガキの頃の自分が
本当はどうしてほしかったかを
remember what you really wanted when you were a brat.
ちゃんと頭っから
思い出してみるんだな
Well then, good night.
じゃ おやすみ
キュッ キュッ
キュッ
"You have to figure it out yourself", huh?
「意味は自分で見つける」 か
I don't get it...
わっかんないなあ～
キュッ キュッ キュッ
That was you just now.
今のチコのマネ
キュ～ッ ？
Huh? No good?
えっ ？ ダメ ？
（九太の母） なりきる
なったつもりで
Become him.
Huh?
Was that you just now?
今の お前？
なりきる
Become him...
Become him.
ふわあああ...
あっ ふわあああ...
What am I doing...?
何やってんだ 俺
I should at least learn the footwork.
せめて足だけでも...
うおりゃ
うおりゃ いててて...
Ow, ow, ow...
What was that?
何だ 何やってんだ？
What are you doing?
Become him.
（九太の母の声） なりきる
なったつもりで
（熊徹・九太） ふんっ
What are you two doing?
（多々良）
何やってんだ お前ら
バカにしてんのか
Are you making a fool of me?!
してねえよ
I'm not!
じゃ何だ ！
Then what are you doing?!
何でもいいだろ ！
None of your business!
フンッ
You're annoying!
うっとうしいんだよ ！
Huh?
あれ？
どこへ行った...
Where did he run off to?
What's up with that?!
何のつもりだ ったく
He's like a duck following its parent.
まるで親鴨と小鴨だな
I'm not a duck!
俺は鴨じゃねえ
子が親をマネて育つのは
当然だろう
Isn't it normal for a child to imitate his parent?
I'm not his parent.
俺は親じゃねえ
Kyuuta intends to learn from you from scratch.
九太はイチから
お前に習うつもりなんだよ
Like a baby following his parent.
親を追う赤ん坊のように
赤ん坊？
A baby?
フン
（百秋坊） ふん 熊徹め
まんざらでもない様子だ
Kumatetsu doesn't seem dissatisfied.
No parent would be unhappy about his child trying to become like him.
マネされて うれしくない親は
いないというが
はたして...
Hey brat, how long are you going to continue this farce?
おい ガキ
いつまで茶番を続ける気だよ
If imitating someone could make you stronger, there'd be no hardships!
マネっこで強くなるなら
苦労はねえぜ
（熊徹） おい 邪魔すんな
Hey, don't distract us!
Huh?
は？ おめえ
うっとうしいって あれほど...
Weren't you really annoyed by it?
（熊徹） いいからあっち行け ！
It's fine, just go away!
Hey, hey...
いつから あいつは
人が変わっちまったんだい
What's up with him?
さあてね
I don't know.
素直な弟子が
かわいくなったんだろう
Maybe he's warmed up to his sincere disciple.
へっ あの野郎
そんなタマじゃ...
No way...
マジでか？
Seriously?!
（熊徹） ほら
Here!
All right, I get it!
（多々良） おう だったらよ
じゃこれでどうだい ！
Then how about this?!
Perfect!
おっ キター ！
No, time out!
（多々良） ちょっとタンマ
タンマ タンマ
No time outs!
（熊徹） タンマなし
ちょっと待て 待て
ちょちょ返せ...
Wait, give that back!
Nope!
待たねえ へへへ
（多々良） あーあ
あれ？
Huh?
Even though I'm not looking,
見てないのに
わかる
I know.
I know!
わかる ！
Damn!
（多々良） チキショ ー
Should I try it out?
試すか
（熊徹） いえっ
いてっ
Ow!
Ow, ow, ow...
（熊徹） いてっ...
（百秋坊） どうした 九太
What's wrong, Kyuuta?
What are you doing?!
何しやがる やめろ
Stop, stop!
やめろ ！
Huh?
What's happening?
どうなってんだ？
九太 お前...
Kyuuta, you...
I kept observing his footwork,
ずっと足だけ見て
マネしてたら
suddenly I could tell what he'd do next.
なんとなく次の足が
わかるようになった
What?!
なに ？ ふざけんな...
Stop joking!
こりゃてえしたもんだ 九太 ！
That's amazing, Kyuuta!
You just made me admire you for the first time!
初めて おめえに
感心させられちまったぜ
Kumatetsu, you better learn from Kyuuta.
熊徹 おめえも
九太に習うがいいぜ
Learn from him?!
習うだと ？
Why would I?!
なぜ俺が ！
（九太） 教えてやってもいいぜ
I don't mind teaching you.
Huh?!
In return...
その代わり
Huh?!
I have no idea how to hold a sword or throw a punch,
剣の持ち方とかパンチとか
全然わかんねえから
教えてくれよ
so please teach me!
Ow!
いてっ ！
Damn, explain it in more detail!
くそーっ もっと
ちゃんと教えろ ！
いてっ ！
Ow!
Observe your opponent and become one with him.
相手をよく見て合わせる
Ow!
（熊徹） いてっ...
（九太） 合わせる
Become one!
That's what Kumatetsu gets for never paying attention to anyone but himself.
熊徹の奴
周りのことにゃ
お構いなしの
自分勝手様だからな
相手に合わすなんざ
一番 苦手なことよ
Understanding his enemy is the thing he's worst at.
１ 人で強くなった報いだ
That's the drawback of becoming strong all by yourself.
Ow!
いてっ
Become one with your opponent!
相手に合わせるんだよ
やってるよ いてっ
That's what I'm doing!
You can't do it at all!
できてないだろ
Acting all high and mighty, you...!
えらそうに この...
Explain it in more detail.
もっとちゃんと教えろ
やあっ
いっつー
うりゃあ ！
Damn!
くっそー ！
（男の子１ ） とりゃ うっ
おおっ あわわ...
Don't get full of yourself!
調子に乗るなよ
I'm betting on Jiroumaru.
俺 二郞丸
Me as well.
Me, too.
俺も二郞丸
おら おら おっ おっ...
Take this!
えい おら おら
ほら ほら
おら おら おら おら
おら おら おら...
You're amazing!
お前 すげえな
I like strong people!
（二郎丸） オイラ
強い奴が好きなんだ
Come over to my place next time!
今度 うちに遊びに来いよ
We have lots of tasty sweets!
うまい菓子 いっぱいあるぞ
So come over, 'kay?
だから遊びに来いって
やあっ
I did it!
やった ！
おりゃあ ！
くっそー ！
Damn!
Just take your time when you're eating...
お前ら ゆっくり
食えっつってんだろ
勝った ！
洗いもんしとけよ
I win!
You do the dishes!
くそっ
Damn!
You've grown quite a bit.
（百秋坊） ずいぶん背が伸びたな
You think so, Hyaku-san?
そうかな 百さん
Eh?
Tata-san?
多々さん
いつの間に ？ マジかよ
When did this happen...
Seriously?
（猪王山） ほう
まともな形になっている
His form is decent.
It seems so.
（宗師） そのようじゃ
For a human, his progress is astonishing.
人間の子供を
よくぞあそこまで
はて おぬしでも
気づかんか
Haven't you noticed?
Huh?
より成長しておるのは
熊徹の方じゃ
The one who progressed the most is Kumatetsu.
洗練されて
キレが増しておる
His movements are refined and sharp.
Indeed.
確かに ！
You can't tell which one's the master.
どちらが師匠か
わからんのう
ムフォ フォ フォ フォ フォ...
九太 お前いくつになった ？
Kyuuta, how old are you now?
I see, then you're Jyuunanata from now on.
"17th boy"
そうか ならお前は
今から十七太だ
Kyuuta is fine.
九太で結構だ
Master Kumatetsu!
（若者） 熊徹師匠 どうか俺を
弟子にしてください
Please take me as your disciple!
I'd like to become strong like Kyuuta-san!
俺も九太さんみたいに
強くなりたいっす
All right, nice determination.
よーし なかなかいい覚悟だ
（若者） ありがとうございます ！
Thank you very much!
（多々良） じゃあ あの列並んで
（若者） え？
Well then, go line up.
Eh?!
Wait at the end of the line until you're called!
（多々良） 最後尾で口利き料を
準備して待つがよい
They're all still green behind the ears
and don't seem to have what it takes.
どいつもこいつも
ハナタレばっかりで
モノになりそうもねえな
Hm?
I decide what I practice!
自分の稽古は自分で決める ！
いいや 俺が決める ！
No, I do!
九太はもう大人だ
大人扱いしてやれ
Kyuuta's already an adult, treat him like one.
こいつを ？
He is?
毛も生えてない
ツルツルのくせに
He doesn't even have any fur!
毛ぐらい生えてる
I do have fur!
Where?!
（熊徹） どこが生えてんだ ！
（百秋坊） おいおい
Now, now...
I win!
勝った ！ じゃあな
See ya!
Wait!
待て ！
I'm not done talking!
話は終わってねえ
You do the dishes!
洗いもんしとけよ
（熊徹） 待て この野郎 ！
Wait, damnit!
よう 九太 うち寄ってけ ！
Hey Kyuuta, let's go to our place!
後で ！
Later!
I told you to wait!
こら 待て
Kyuuta really is something.
大したもんだぜ 九太は
Thanks to him, Kumatetsu has improved a lot.
おかげで熊徹庵は大繁盛
うちの見廻組もウカウカ
してられないって父ちゃんが...
Dad said that our unit can't let its guard down.
Kumatetsu?
（一郎彦） 熊徹？
あんな半端者と父上を
比べるな
Don't compare such a blockhead with father.
Huh?
あ ？ どうした 兄ちゃん
What's wrong, Nii-chan?
何でもない
It's nothing.
おっと どこ行った
Whoops!
Where'd he go?!
ええい
（九太） ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ...
Geez, he's really stubborn.
ったく あいつ
しつこいんだから
キュッ
あれ？ ここは...
Huh? This is...
The important thing is...
（九太） かんじんの...
only so... because...
などを... にして...
くっつけて... るのだが...
you keep it close...
その... の... は...
That is so...
because... you had it... for a long time...
の... ながく...
い... から...
ねえ
Say...
how do you read this?
これ 何て読む？
"Whale".
（少女） 鯨
Oh, so it's "whale".
ああ クジラか
I told you so!
（男子高校生 １ ） 俺 言ったじゃん
（男子高校生２） 言ったっけ ？
Dunno what you mean!
（男子高校生 １ ） 知らねーよ
（女子高校生 １ ） もううるさい～
Shut up already!
（女子高校生 １ ）
もしもし ？ あ 切れた
Hello?
They hung up!
Who was it?
誰これ？
No idea.
わかんない
（女子高校生 １ ） 何？
What is it?
If you're gonna be noisy, do it outside.
（少女） 騒ぐなら外に行きなよ
（女子高校生 １ ）
外なら何してもいいの？
Can I do whatever I want outside?
That's up to you.
それは あなたたちの自由でしょ
（女子高校生 １ ） 行こ
Let's go.
She wouldn't shut up since first class, so everyone ignores her.
（女子高校生 １ ） こいつ
１ 年の時からウザくて
みんなに無視されてんの
Huh... So we can do whatever we want?
（女子高校生２） へー
じゃ何やってもいいよね
Hey, don't run away!
おい 逃げんなよ
Stop it!
（少女） やめて
（女子高校生 １ ）
外なら何してもいいんでしょ
I can do whatever I want outside, right?!
We're not bothering anyone after all!
（女子高校生２）
誰にも迷惑かけてませんから
（女子高校生 １ ） 動かない
Don't move...
Oh, you saw that?
（男子高校生 １ ） あー 見てた ？
Ah, you see, there was some trouble.
いや ちょっと トラブルでさ
You didn't see anything, did you?! Huh?!
なんも見てねえよな なっ ？
くそが ！
You piece of shit!
What's with that look?
何だよ その顔
What's up with his clothes?
何 あいつの格好 ダサッ ！
They're lame!
ダサッ アハハ...
So lame!
行こ
Let's go.
Yeah.
進学校はみんな仲良しなんて
ウソだよ
It's a lie that everyone gets along in a new school.
暴力はよくない でもーー
Violence is bad.
However, thank you for saving me.
ありがとう 助けてくれて
I didn't really save you.
（九太） 別に助けてない
（少女） 助けてくれたじゃん
You did save me.
ねえ これ何て読む？
Say, how do you read this?
I don't know anything.
何にも知らないんだ
小学校から学校行ってない
I haven't been to school since primary school.
Really?
ホン トに ？
In that case, I'll teach you all the characters in that book.
じゃあーー
その本にある字
私が全部教える
Really?
ホン ト ？
Yes.
I'm Kaede.
私 「かえで」
It's written with the characters "tree" and "wind", "Kaede".
木に風って書いて 楓
I'm... Ren.
俺は蓮
The characters for Ren are...
蓮って字は...
（楓） 草冠に連なる
"Tsuranaru" with a "grass" radical.
Right...
そう
Ren-kun.
蓮くん
（熊徹） ハックシュン ！
"Break on through the-
Break oｎ ｔhrough ｔo ｔhe. . .
（熊徹） 九太 ！
Kyuuta! Kyuuta!
九太 ！
Shut up!
うるせえ
（熊徹） 遅い
（九太） どなるな
Too slow!
Don't yell!
Kyuuta!
（熊徹） 九太 ！
He's long gone.
とっくに出かけたぜ
He seems busy lately.
ここのところ
忙しくしているようだが
Busy with what?!
何にだ？
（楓） 主人公は自分の片足を
奪った憎いクジラに
The protagonist wants revenge on the whale who took his leg.
復讐しようとしている
But the protagonist is actually fighting against himself.
でも実は主人公は
自分自身と
闘っているんじゃないかな
Against himself?
（九太） 自分自身？
It means the whale is a reflection of himself.
（楓） つまりクジラは
自分を映す鏡で
Reflection...
（九太） 鏡...
（楓） すごい集中力
この調子なら
Your concentration is incredible.
At this rate, you should be able to solve the problems in the reference book in no time.
すぐに私の参考書の問題も
解けるかもね
It's because you're a good teacher.
（九太） 楓の教え方がうまいんだ
Really?
ホン ト ？
I have a bossy master, so I can tell.
師匠には ちょっと
うるさい俺が言うんだ
間違いない
By master, do you mean the kendo master who raised you?
（楓） 師匠さんって育ててくれた
剣道の師匠さん？
（九太） ダメ師匠
He's useless.
フッ 仲いいんだね
You must be close.
（九太）
まさか どなり合ってばっか
No way, we always fight.
Sounds nice, I'm jealous.
いいな うらやましい
Why?
（九太） なんで？
I don't ever fight with my parents.
私... 親とケンカしたこともない
Huh?
親の幸せのために
私がいる
I'm here for the happiness of my parents.
Since kindergarten, I desperately tried to get the grades my parents wanted.
幼稚園から受験して
父さんと母さんが
望むような成績を
死にもの狂いで取って
Yet they don't know how I feel.
なのに ２人とも
私の気持ちなんて知らない
They don't even notice.
気づいてすらいない
But I know.
でもわかってる
Unless I find out who I am by myself,
私は私自身で
私を見つけなきゃ
本当の私になれない
it won't be really me.
So even though it's difficult right now, I study hard.
だから今はつらくても
必死で勉強して
学費免除されるくらいの成績で
大学に受かったら
Once I graduate and make it into a university, I'll move out.
家を出る
After that, I'll study only for myself.
それからは
自分のためだけに勉強して
Graduate out of my own strength.
自分の力で卒業して
そして自分の人生を生きる
And then, live my own life.
ハァー
I've never told this to anyone before.
誰かに初めて本亯が言えた
スッキリ した ！
I feel relieved.
Kaede...
楓...
Hey, about that book...
ねえ その本のことだけど
（楓） 私が教えるだけじゃ
限りがあるよ
There are limits to what I can teach.
もっとしっかりと
読みこなす方法を学べる先生が
I'm sure there are even better teachers.
きっといる
Where?
どこに ？
Ren-kun, would you like to go to university?
蓮くん 大学行く気ある？
That's...
そんな...
（楓） 受験するなら
サポー トするよ
I'll help you with the entrance exams!
But me going to university...
でも大学なんて俺...
Don't you want to know more about the things you don't know?
知らないことを
もっとたくさん知りたくない？
知りたい
I do.
"Kounin" is the certificate people
who're at high school graduate level can get.
（楓） 「高認」
高等学校卒業程度認定試験
ていう制度があるのね
It used to be called "daiken", it's a university entrance test for people who didn't graduate from high school.
昔は 「大検」 っていって
高校に行ってなくても
大学を受験できる資格試験で...
無理でしょ
It's impossible.
Huh?
I don't know your proficiency,
どんな学力か知らないけど
but if you've been a shut-in till you're this old,
その年まで
引きこもってたんなら
まずは夜間中学からでも
始めたら ？
how about starting with evening middle school?
（楓） あ ですが...
Ah, but...
Life isn't that easy.
そんなに世の中
甘いもんじゃないよ
万が一受かっても
保護者の援助なくて
Even if you were accepted, without a guardian,
学費どうするの？
what about the tuition payments?
奨学金だって
よっぽどじゃなきゃ
Even scholarships are hard to get nowadays.
今どき貸してくれないでしょ
But...
（楓） あの しかし...
I totally get it!
よくわかりました ！
I knew university would be impossible for me...
やっぱ無理だよ 大学なんて
（女性職員） ごめんね～
I apologise for that!
Feel free to consult me.
何でも相談して
There are quite a few universities with scholarship systems.
特待制度のある大学も
少なくないし
返済不要の企業奨学金も
紹介できるから
You can also arrange a corporate scholarship which you don't need to pay back.
もちろん成績次第だけど
Dependant on your grades, of course.
あ ありがとうございます ！
Thank you very much!
Thank you very much.
ありがとう... ございます
（九太） 数学と理科も必修
Math and science are compulsory.
I haven't studied them at all.
まったく勉強してないけど
Leave it to me, I'll teach you everything!
任せて しっかり
私が教えるから
We need a certificate of residence for the Kounin test.
（戸籍係） 高認受験のため
住民票が必要とのことですが
It seems your former certificate has been erased.
元の住民票は職権で
削除されているようです
I knew it...
（九太） やっぱり...
But since there are still records of your family register,
ですが戸籍の附票に
記録が残っていますので
we can register a new certificate of residence.
新しく住民票を登録できます
お父様の現住所の記載に
間違いがないか
Is your father's current address correct?
Please verify it.
確認してください
The father you were separated from?
（楓） 離れて暮らしてた
お父さん？
I had no idea where he was.
（九太） どこにいるか
全然知らなかった
But to find him this easily...
でも こんなに簡単に
わかるなんて
（楓） 会いに行く ？
Are you going to meet him?
I might be a bother if I suddenly went there.
（九太） いきなり行っても
迷惑かもしれないし
He might have forgotten about me.
もう忘れちゃってるかも
しれないし
But...
でも...
What should I write...
（九太） 何て書けば...
Dad, throw the ball!
（息子） お父さん ボール
（父親） ハハッ ほれっ
Here!
（店員） お客さん 忘れ物
Sir, you forgot something.
（男） あっ
ホン トだ ついうっかり
Really, how careless of me.
どうもありがとう
Thank you very much.
（店員） どうも
You're welcome.
Um...
あの...
Yes?
はい？
俺のこと 覚えてますか？
Do you... remember... me?
やっぱり
I knew it...
すいません
I'm sorry.
Ren?
蓮？
Are you Ren?
蓮なのか？
（九太の父） こんなに大きくなって
You've grown so much,
how could I tell?!
わかんねえよ
Where were you till now?!
どうしてたんだよ 今まで
Oh, um, I was with people who were taking care of me, and...
あ... その...
世話んなった人がいて
それで...
I'm glad you're all right...
（九太の父） よかった 無事で
I'm sorry...
すまなかった
I couldn't do anything for you all this time...
今まで何にもしてやれなくて
Dad...
父さん
I see.
（楓） そう... よかったね
I'm happy for you.
（九太） 父さん 母さんのこと
ずっと後になって知ったんだって
It turns out dad didn't find out about mum until a lot later.
行方不明の俺をずっと捜して
He kept looking for me.
Even after the police gave up, he still continued.
警察が諦めた後でも
あちこち捜してくれてたって
（楓） そう...
I see.
Kaede!
（友達 １ ） 楓 ！
Say, is that your boyfriend?
ねえ その人 楓の彼氏？
（楓） 違うよ
He's not!
Then who's he?
（友達２） じゃ誰？
（友達３） どこの学校？
Which school is he from?
（楓） あっち行ってて ！
Go away!
ごめん
Sorry.
I wonder if I can also live an ordinary life now.
これで俺も
普通になれるかな？
Ordinary?
普通？
Live with my parents like an ordinary person.
（九太） 普通の奴みたいに
親と一緒にいて
Study and work like an ordinary person.
普通に勉強したり
働いたり して
Come home and sleep like an ordinary person.
普通に家に帰って
普通に寝る
Maybe I can live like that, too.
そんな生き方 ひょっとしたら
俺にもあるのかな
Are you hesitating?
でも... 迷ってる？
（楓） 師匠さんのこと ？
Is it because of your master?
Where have you been?
（熊徹） どこ行ってた
I want to talk about something, listen seriously.
（九太） 相談があるんだ
真剣に聞いてほしい
（熊徹） 稽古はどうした
How is your training?
Listen, the thing is...
（九太） 聞いて 実は...
You think you can neglect it?
（熊徹） サボっていいと
思ってるのか
（百秋坊） 聞いてやれ 熊徹
Listen to him, Kumatetsu.
And what's this?
それより何だ こりゃ
I found it in your bed.
お前の寝床にあった
説明してみろ
Explain.
I want to go to a human school.
人間の学校に行きたい
Huh?!
I want to know more about the other world, so...
他の世界を知りたい だから...
Aren't there more important things you should do?
（熊徹） そんなことより お前にゃ
もっとやることがあるだろ
Didn't you want to become strong?
強くなるのが
お前の目的じゃねえのか
I've become strong.
強くなったよ
は？ 笑かすな
Huh?! Don't make me laugh!
Kumatetsu.
（百秋坊） 熊徹
I've become plenty strong.
十分 強くなった
What part of you is strong, huh?!
おめえのどこが
強いってんだ あ ？
あんたと話すと
いっつもこうなるよな
Talking with you always ends up like this...
俺の話も聞かず
自分ばっか勝手にわめいて
You ignore what I say and act selfish.
Tell me, when did you become strong?!
言ってみろ ！
いつ強くなったんだ？
That's enough.
（九太） もういいよ
Wait!
（熊徹） 待て ！ どこ行く
Where are you off to?
There's one more thing.
もう １ つ話がある
I found my father, I'm going there.
父親が見つかった
そこへ行く 今決めた
That's what I just decided.
Wait, wait!
待て
待て ！
Don't go!
行くな
Step aside.
（九太） どけよ
（熊徹） 行かせねえ ！
I won't let you go!
Don't go!
行くな ！
Kyuuta!
九太 ！
Were you able to resolve things?
（楓） 迷ってたの解決した ？
I guess not...
しなかったんだ...
Doesn't matter anymore.
関係ないよ もう
I'm going to meet my dad now, and everything will be fine.
これから父さんと会うんだ
会ったら解決する
無理してない？
Aren't you overdoing it?
Why would I?
なんで俺が？
今日ずっと図書館にいる
何かあったら来て
I'll be at the library today.
Come to me if anything happens.
Wrong!
（熊徹） 違う ！
違う 違う 違う 違う
Wrong, wrong, wrong, wrong!
I'm sorry!
（弟子） すいません
（熊徹） わかるだろ 勘のいい奴なら
Shouldn't you get it if you're a quick learner?
I'm sorry!
（弟子） すいません
Don't apologise for everything!
（熊徹） 何でも謝ってんじゃねえよ
I'm sorry!
（弟子たち） すいません ！
（熊徹） もういい ！
Enough!
ったく どいつもこいつも
Each and every one of them...
To find his father after all this time...
この期に及んで
父親が現れるとはね
Does he really not intend to come back?
本当に
帰ってこないつもりかね？
Why would he come back?
（多々良） 帰ってくるわきゃ
ねえだろ
（百秋坊） ふむ...
Yeah...
Without Kyuuta, Kumatetsu will regress to his former useless self.
九太がいないと熊徹は
元のダメ男に逆戻りだ
No, he's already-
いや もうすでに...
（熊徹） うるせえ ！
Shut up!
何しやがんだ 危ねえな ！
What are you doing?! That's dangerous!
He saw himself as Kyuuta's foster parent.
（百秋坊） あんな奴でも今まで
九太の親代わりの
つもりだったんだよ
He did?
（多々良） あいつが？
Damn!
（熊徹） くそっ
Ren!
蓮 ！
Tonight's dinner is ham omelette!
今日の晩飯 ハム入りオムレツ
Let's prepare it and eat together.
作って一緒に食おう
By the way, could you tell me more about the person who's taken care of you till now?
（九太の父） それはそうと
今までお世話になった人のこと
もっと詳しく教えてくれないか
Huh?
I have to visit him and thank him properly.
ご挨拶しなきゃ
それで ちゃんとお礼をして
After that, we can live together.
それから ２人で一緒に暮らそう
Wait a moment.
ちょっと待って
（九太の父） ん？ 当然だろう
Isn't that obvious?
It just seems a bit sudden...
（九太） だって...
急に埋まんないよ 時間
（九太の父） そっか つい...
I see... I...
Right...
そうだよな
Time flows different for adults and children.
大人の流れる時間と
子供の流れる時間は
違うもんな
The time I spent with you and your mother feels like yesterday to me.
俺には母さんや蓮と
過ごしていたのが
いまだに つい昨日のこと
みたいなんだ
Yesterday?
昨日 ？
Sorry for rushing things.
（九太の父） 急いて悪かったな
少しずつ やり直そう
Let's slowly start over.
We'll forget all the painful things...
今までの辛いことは全部忘れて
これからは
前を向いていけるように
and live facing forward from now on.
Start over what?
（九太） やり直すって何を ？
Why do you decide that it's just painful?
なんで辛いって決めつけるの？
What do you even know about me?!
父さんは俺の何を
知ってるんだよ
蓮...
Ren...
You don't know anything, so don't act like you do!
何にも知らないくせに
知ったようなこと言うなよ ！
Ren, I...
蓮 俺は...
Of course you don't know...
（九太） 知らないの当然だよな
I haven't told you anything...
俺 なんも言ってないし
Sorry, I won't come over today.
ごめん 今日行くのやめとく
And your meal?
（九太の父） メシは？
（九太） いい
No, thanks.
Ren, I don't mind if you decide what we do from now on!
蓮
これからどうするか
蓮が決めればいいよ
But don't forget!
だけど忘れないで
I'll do whatever I can! So...
俺にできることは
何でも全力でする
だから...
Ren!
蓮 ！
What's going on with me?
（九太の声） 何なんだ 俺は
Why did I say those things to dad?
なんで父さんに
あんなこと言っちゃうんだ
行くな
Don't go!
Damn, why am I remembering him?
（九太の声） くそっ
なんであいつなんかが...
Let's start over.
やり直そう
Damn.
（九太の声） くそっ
Don't go!
行くな ！
Damn!
くそっ ！
わっかんねえ
I don't get it!
ハァ ハァ ハァ...
That's...
あれは？
（影） ダイキライ
I hate you.
I hate... you...
ダイ ... キライ ...
The old me?
昔の俺？
A hole?
穴？
あっ 消えた
It disappeared!
ハァ ハァ...
Ren-kun?
（楓） 蓮くん？
You have a really scary look, like you aren't yourself.
すごく怖い顔
蓮くんじゃないみたい
Please tell me, what am I?
（九太） 教えてくれ
俺は一体何なんだ？
人間かな
それともバケモノかな
Am I a human, or am I a beast?
A beast?
（楓） バケモノ ？
Or... am I an ugly monster?
それとも... 醜い怪物かな
What are saying?
（楓） 何言ってるの？
Come on, tell me, what am I?
（九太） 教えてくれ
ねえ 俺は...
Ren-kun, you're not yourself.
蓮くん 普通じゃない
俺は一体...
Just what... am I?!
俺は...
I too am sometimes in so much pain that I don't know what to do.
私も時々
どうしようもなく
苦しくなることがある
No matter what I do,
どうにでもなれって
it feels like something's going to burst in my chest.
何かが胸の中から
噴き出してしまいそうになる
It's not just you.
蓮くんだけじゃない
私だけじゃない
It's not just me.
I'm sure it happens to everyone.
きっと みんなそう
That's why you'll be fine.
だから 大丈夫
That's why...
だから...
大丈夫
you'll be fine!
ありがとう
Thank you.
I've calmed down.
落ち着いた
I'm myself again.
頭冷やす
あっ 待って
Wait.
I've liked this bookmark since I was little.
小さい頃 好きだった本の
しおり
It has helped me many times.
私 これに
ずいぶん助けられたの
If you're ever uncertain of yourself or have feelings like before,
もし自分で
危ないって思ったり
さっきみたいな気持ちに
なったら
remember... this charm.
思い出して
お守り
Huh? What's going on?
（九太） 何だ
どうなってるんだ？
Kyuuta!
（二郎丸） 九太 ！
Let's go to my place.
うち寄ってけよ
宗師様が突然 日にちを
決めたもんだから
The grandmaster has suddenly decided on a day,
街中 大騒ぎさ
so the city is in an uproar.
（九太） 日にち ？
Decided on a day?
（二郎丸の母）
ゆっくり してってね
Take your time.
ありがとう 母ちゃん
Thank you, Mum.
The match between my dad and your master is tomorrow.
明日はオイラの父ちゃんと
お前の師匠の
決着の日だよ
新しい宗師を決める試合の...
The match to decide the new grandmaster.
You didn't know?
まさか知らなかったのか？
実はちょっとモメててさ
We kinda had a fight.
気まずくて
しばらく会ってなくて
It got awkward so I kept my distance.
I see.
そっか...
We haven't seen dad around lately, either.
でもオイラも父ちゃんの顔
見てないぜ
He's been busy training.
ずっと稽古で忙しいからな
I miss him, but it can't be helped.
寂しいけど しょうがない
You don't want your master to lose either, right?
お前もお前の師匠が
負けたらイヤだろ？
So just forget about that awkward stuff and cheer him on.
なら気まずいなんて
言ってないで応援しようぜ
Yeah.
Regardless of the outcome, we remain friends.
どっちになっても
オイラたちは友達だ
Of course.
もちろん
I hope it's a good match.
（二郎丸）
いい試合になるといいな
Yeah.
Jiroumaru!
（一郎彦） 二郎丸
Nii-chan!
兄ちゃん
Kyuuta might be troubled if you keep him occupied for too long.
（一郎彦） あまり引き留めて
九太に迷惑をかけてはいけないぞ
You hear that?
ほら もうヒグラシが鳴いている
Even the cicadas started chirping.
I'll walk him to the entrance.
僕が玄関まで送っていこう
Thanks. Well then...
ありがとう じゃ
（一郎彦） 何が... いい試合だ
What... good match?!
The outcome... is already... obvious!
勝敗など... 端から...
決まっているだろ
A human like you...
人間のお前や...
熊徹みたいな... 半端者は
A blockhead... like Kumatetsu...
半端者らしく...
分をわきまえろ ！
Know your places as the blockheads you are!
Ichirouhiko...
一郎彦...
（一郞彦） フン
Why does he have the same thing...?
（九太） なぜ俺と同じ...
Why...?
なぜ？
Which one are you rooting for?
あんた どっち
応援してんの？
I'm not sure.
どっちかな
I'm betting on Iouzen.
俺 猪王山
俺 熊徹
I'm betting on Kumatetsu.
I...
俺は... ああっ 悩む ！
How worrying!
I've been worrying.
わしは悩んだ
この９年 悩んで悩んで
また悩んだが
For the past nine years, I've been worrying, worrying, worrying.
And I have finally reached a decision.
ようやく決めたぞよ
So, what kind of god are you going to become?
それで何の神様に
おなりになるんですかい？
Definitely the god of decisiveness!
ズバリ 決断力の神じゃ
The reincarnation ritual will be held after the match.
試合後に
転生の儀式を行うので
楽しみにせよ
Enjoy it.
The match to select the next grandmaster will now commence!
（審判長） これより渋天街の
新しい宗師を
決する儀式を行う
The candidates shall step forward!
候補者は前へ
Woah!
There's a huge difference in the expressions of your disciples!
弟子の面だけで
明らかに見劣り してるな
If only Kyuuta were here.
九太がいてくれたらな
Kumatetsu, don't look so gloomy, the match is about to begin!
熊徹 浮かねえ顔すんなよ
これから試合だぜ
ええい
Be quiet!
うるせえな
In accordance to the rules, the swords shall remain sheathed.
（審判長） 作法に則り
刀は鞘のまま使用すること
Unsheathing them won't be forgiven!
抜くことは許されない
逃げた者は負け
Running away results in a loss.
Remaining down by the count of ten results in a loss.
または十拍の間
失神した者は負け
その他 作法規則を順守すること
We shall bear witness to the compliance of these rules.
Candidates, prepare!
両者 用意 ！
Begin!
始め ！
Out of nowhere?!
いきなりかよ
熊徹が押してる
Kumatetsu is pushing him back.
Even though he lacks stamina!
あの野郎 スタミナも考えずに
オラアー
Dad!
父ちゃん ！
Shut up and keep watching!
（一郞彦） 黙って見てろ
See?!
（一郞彦） ほら見ろ
くそっ
Damn!
As expected of father!
（一郎彦） さすが父上
（熊徹） どわっ
This is bad...
まじいな
ムダにやられおって
He keeps getting hit...
This is...
こりゃあ...
Has it been decided?
決まりかのう
Are you finished already, Kumatetsu?!
もう終わりかよ 熊徹 ！
ハァ... ハッ
ウオアアアー ！
（審判長） ひとつ ！
One!
ふたつ ！
Two!
Three!
みっつ ！
Four!
よっつ ！
Five!
いつつ ！
（審判長） むっつ ！
（九太） くそっ
Six!
Damn!
Seven!
（審判長） ななつ ！
Eight!
やっつ ！
Kyuuta!
九太 ！
N-
It's Kyuuta!
（バケモノ２１） 九太だ
（バケモノ２２） 熊徹の一番弟子だ
He's Kumatetsu's best disciple.
（バケモノ２３） あいつが？
He is?
九太...
Kyuuta...
あっ 九太 頼む
Please Kyuuta, cheer Kumatetsu on!
熊徹を勇気づけてくれ
What are you doing, you dumbass?!
何やってんだ バカ野郎 ！
Stand up already!
とっとと立て ！
Didn't you leave?
おめえ 出てったくせに
よくノコノコ 顔出せるな
How dare you show your face now?
And what's with your stupid shape?!
あんたこそ
何だ そのマヌケな姿は ！
What did you say?!
（熊徹） 何だと この野郎
（九太） みっともねえ
Pathetic!
This isn't the time to be swearing at each other!
こんな時に
ののしり合いはやめろ
What?!
You look miserable!
Gimme a break!
勘弁してくれ
どうしてあいつらは
いつもこうなんだ
Why does it always turn out like this?!
Stop being depressed!
しょぼくれてんじゃねえ
Get up by yourself already!
１ 人でもさっさと勝て ！
へンッ
Even without you butting in, I won't lose!
おめえなんかが
しゃしゃり出ねえでも
負けねえんだ...
What?!
なに ？
（熊徹） うらっ
He intends to continue?
まだやる気とは
This just got interesting.
面白うなってきたわい
One to the right!
そこ 右 ！
Dodge! Counter!
スウェー カウンター
You almost have him!
イケる 中段 ！
Look, he's laughing.
見ろよ あいつ笑ってやがる
It's the face he makes when he trains with Kyuuta.
九太と一緒に
稽古してる時の顔だ
Are you saying, even though he's in the middle of a match...
まさか 試合中だってえのに
His spirit has transcended beyond the enemy in front of him!
（賢者１ ） あやつの心は今
目の前の相手を
超越した場所におる
He is in a state of perfect concentration.
まさに完全なる集中
無我の境地
Kumatetsu alone can't win.
熊徹１ 人なら勝ち目はない
But I can't tell the outcome when they're together!
じゃが... ２人ならわからんぞ
Dad, hang in there!
父ちゃん がんばれ
Ahh, he'll lose!
ああっ 負けちゃう ！
（一郎彦） 黙れ ！
Shut up!
N-Nii-chan?
兄ちゃん？
Kyuuta...!
九太
That bastard, even though he's just a human...!
（一郞彦）
あの野郞 人間のくせに ！
Don't get pushed back!
押し込まれんな
競り負けんな
Push back instead!
Use your ridiculous strength!
馬鹿力 出せ ！
Now!
What?!
なに ？
わあっ ！
Right there!
そこだああ...
（審判長） ひとつ ！
One!
Two!
ふたつ ！
Three!
みっつ ！
Four!
よっつ ！
Five!
いつつ ！
Six!
むっつ ！
Seven!
ななつ ！
Eight!
やっつ ！
Nine!
ここのつ ！
Ten!
とお ！
The winner has been decided!
勝負は決した ！
It's Kumatetsu!
熊徹 ！
Don't make me worry.
ヒヤヒヤさせんな
心配しろなんて
頼んでねえよ
I didn't ask you to.
I'm glad you could win.
よく勝てたもんだぜ
Of course I'd win.
勝つに決まってるだろ
Stop joking, you barely made it.
バカ言え
へロへロだったくせに
Shut up.
うるせえ
It's the birth of a new grandmaster!
（バケモノ２４）
新しい宗師の誕生だ ！
Banzai! Banzai!
ばんざーい ばんざーい
He's got a good son.
いい息子だ
Huh?
（弟子 １ ） は？
Let's go.
行くぞ
The sword is... gone?
剣が... ない？
What is this red stuff?
この赤えのは何だ？
え？ 九太
Huh, Kyuuta?
どうなってんだ？
What's going on?
父上 ！
Father, the match was decided with my telekinesis and your sword!
私の念動力と父上の剣で
勝負をつけました
あなたの勝ちです ！
It's your win!
There's no way you'd lose to that blockhead, after all!
あんな半端者に父上が
負けるわけがありませんからね
Isn't that right, Kyuuta?
そうだろ 九太
そうだろ ！
Isn't that right?!
Stop, Ichirouhiko!
やめろ 一郎彦 ！
Father, I'm going to finish him off now.
父上 今からとどめです
見てください
Please watch me.
Did you see that, Kyuuta?!
見たか 九太
ざまあねえ
Serves you right!
いいか 勝者は我が父
猪王山だ ！
Do you get it?!
My father, Iouzen, is the winner!
You idiot, you think I'd accept something like this?!
バカ者 ！ そんなことが
認められるか
（一郞彦） アーハハハハハ...
ハハハハハ...
Wh-What's that?!
な... 何だ ありゃあ ？
穴？
A hole?
You can't, Kyuuta!
いかん 九太 ！
How dare you...
よくも...
Kyuuta, reject the darkness!
九太 闇を拒絶せよ
Nii-chan!
兄ちゃん ！
Please stop, Kyuuta!
やめてくれ 九太
What a disaster!
ああっ 最悪だ ！
キュッ
Kyuuta...
（一郎彦の声） 九太
お前...
you...
Ichirouhiko is being consumed by the darkness!
闇が一郞彦を取り込んでおる
I won't forgive you...
（一郎彦の声） 許サナイ
Nii-chan, where are you?
兄ちゃん？
どこ ？ 兄ちゃん ！
Nii-chan!
ハァ... ハァ... ハァ...
Hey... why are you sleeping...?
おい
何... 寝てんだよ...
Wake... up...
起き... ろ...
Kyuuta.
（熊徹） 九太
九太 ！
Kyuuta!
Too slow!
遅い ！
Too slow, too slow, too slow, too slow!
遅い 遅い 遅い 遅い
What are you doing?!
何やってんだ
稽古するぞ オラアッ
It's time for training!
キュッ キュッ キュッ
キュッ
Chiko...
チコ
（チコ） キュッ キュッ キュ～
What is it, Chiko?
どうした ？ チコ
（チコ） キュッ...
（猪王山） すまん 一郎彦
I'm sorry...
Ichirouhiko, I'm sorry...
すまん
（宗師） 一郎彦のあの力は
Ichirouhiko's telekinesis is by no means the ability of a beast.
バケモノの念動力などでは
決してない
It is clearly a power that stems from the darkness within a human heart.
明らかに
人間の胸にのみ宿る闇が
生み出した力じゃ
Grandmaster, you already knew?
（猪王山） 宗師様 以前から
気づいておられたのですか
Iouzen, tell me your reason.
猪王山 訳を話してみよ
His real parents must have had quite the circumstances.
（猪王山） 本当の親には
よっぽどの事情が
あったんだろう
I decided to hide it from everyone and raise him secretly.
皆に隠して
密かに育てると決めた
I knew that humans can harbour darkness in their hearts,
人間が胸に闇を宿すことは
知っていたが
but I thought it'd be fine if I raise him myself.
自分が育てれば大丈夫と考えた
それが今にして思えば
慢心だった
Thinking back, I realise how conceited that was.
自分の驕りだった
It was my own arrogance.
Why don't I have tusks like you?
（一郞彦） どうして私は
父上のように
牙が生えないのですか？
Don't worry, I'm sure they'll grow one day.
（猪王山） 心配するな
いつか生えてくる
Why isn't my nose long like yours?
（一郞彦） どうして
私の鼻は父上のように
長く伸びないのですか？
（猪王山） 案ずるな そのうち
Don't worry, with time...
Father, just what am I...?
（一郞彦） 父上 私は一体...
（猪王山） 一郎彦
お前は私の子だ
Ichirouhiko, you're none other than my son.
他の誰でもない
私 猪王山の息子だよ
You're the son of Iouzen.
The more he believed he was the son of a beast,
（宗師） バケモノの子だと
信じさせようとすればするほど
the more insecure Ichirouhiko became.
一郎彦は
自分自身を信用できず
闇を深くしてしまったのじゃ
That's how the darkness in him was born.
To think our world's ambiance caused the hole in a humans heart to grow to this extent...
バケモノの世界の空気が
人間の胸の穴をあれほど
露わにしてしまうとは
What's this darkness?
（二郎丸） 闇って何だい？
I'm stupid, so I don't get it.
オイラ バカだから
わかんねえよ
It doesn't matter where my brother came from.
兄ちゃんがどっから来たか
なんて知らない
To me, he's just my brother!
オイラにとっちゃ
兄ちゃんは兄ちゃんだ
Jiroumaru!
二郎丸...
宗師様 私たちはもう
Grandmaster, will we be unable to live with Ichirouhiko anymore?
一郎彦と一緒に住むことは
かなわないのでしょうか
Won't we be able to start things over?
もう一度やり直すことは
できないのでしょうか
Ichirouhiko is roaming around somewhere as we speak.
一郎彦は今もどこかを
さまよっておる
As long as the darkness isn't expelled, there's nothing we can do.
あの闇を一郞彦から
追い出さぬ限り
何事もあり得ぬじゃろう
（多々良） 九太
Kyuuta.
You shouldn't get involved in this.
熊徹のこと ほっておく気かよ
バカ者 ！
You idiot!
Do you want revenge?!
敵討ちのつもりか
What good will that do?!
そんなことをして何になる？
H-Hey, Hyakushuubou?
（多々良） お... おい 百秋坊
（百秋坊） もう我慢ならん
I can't hold it in anymore!
You're gravely mistaken if you think I'll be lenient like usual!
私がいつまでも甘い顔を
してると思ったら
大間違いだ ！
Don't you understand after seeing
Kumatetsu in that state, you fool?!
熊徹のあの姿を見て
何も学ばぬか
この愚か者め ！
それでも行くと言うのか
You're still going?
I appreciate your scolding.
ありがとう 叱ってくれて
Thanks to you, I can stand proud.
おかげで背筋がしゃんと伸びた
However, it's not revenge I want.
ただね 敵討ちとは違うんだ
Ichirouhiko and I are the same.
俺と一郞彦は同じで
There's no doubt I could have ended up like him, too.
俺は間違えたら一郎彦みたいに
なっていたかもしれない
It's thanks to the people who raised me that I didn't.
そうならずに済んだのは
俺を育ててくれた
たくさんの人たちのおかげだよ
It's thanks to Tata-san, Hyaku-san, and everyone else.
多々さんや百さんや
みんなの...
Kyuuta, you...
九太 お前...
だからって
他人事にはできないんです
That doesn't mean I can act as if this doesn't concern me.
Ichirouhiko's problem is also my problem.
一郎彦の問題は
俺の問題でもあるから
That's why... I'm going.
だから...
俺は行きます
Please take care of Kumatetsu.
あいつのこと
よろしく頼んます
（多々良） ああ わかった ！
That was splendid!
お前の覚悟は
よっくわかったよ
I totally get your determination!
熊徹のことは任しとけ
Leave Kumatetsu to us!
I won't take my eyes off him!
しっかり見といてやるよ
だから行ってこい
So you can go! Go!
行ってこい ！
（百秋坊） 「自分を育ててくれた
たくさんの人たち」 か
"It's thanks to the people who raised me", huh?
そん中に
俺たちも入っているとはな
For us to be included...
Well, we have been with him since he was little.
九太が小さな頃から
ずっと一緒にいたからな
Yeah.
ああ 最初は生意気で
イヤなガキでな
He was an impertinent, unpleasant brat at first.
雨の日も風の日も
懲りもせず毎日 通って...
Whether it's been rainy or windy,
we've been visiting him every day.
Even though we were looking after him,
面倒みてやってるのに
ありがてえなんて顔
ひとつしねえで
he'd never say a word of thanks.
And he's grown up before we even knew it.
それが気づいてみたら
あんなに大きくなって
いっぱしの口を
ききやがるんだから
He's still cheeky, though.
I'm so proud.
誇らしいのう
Me, too.
誇らしいぜ
（多々良） 熊徹 ！
Kumatetsu!
Ren-kun.
（楓） 蓮くん
（ＴＶの声） 東京株式市埸で
日経平均株価は
小幅に値を上げました
前日のアメリカ
ニューヨーク株式市場で
ダウ平均株価が
値下がりしたことや
日経平均株価が
高値を更新したことで
ひとまず利益を
確定しようという動きから...
I want to give this to you.
（九太） これ 預かっていてほしい
Why?
なんで？
What for?
どうして ？
There's an opponent I have to settle things with.
決着をつけなきゃ
ならない相手がいる
I don't know if I can win.
勝てるかわからない
If I lose, everything might be over.
負けたら何もかも
終わるかもしれない
だから...
That's why...
No way...
そんな...
I'm glad I got to know you.
楓と会えてよかった
楓がいてーー
Thanks to you, I got to learn a lot of new things.
知らないことを
たくさん知ることができた
You made me think, "the world is really big".
世界って広いんだなって
ホン トに思えたんだ
何言ってるの？
これからまだ...
What are you saying?
We still...
Studying together made me really happy.
一緒に勉強できて
俺 うれしかったんだよ
That's why I wanted to thank you.
だから ありがとうって
言いたくて
Wait...
待って
I don't want that!
イヤだよ 私 ！
That's not what I want...
そんなのイヤだよ...
キュッ
Kyuuta...!
（一郞彦） 九太
I won't forgive you.
許サナイ
Even though you're just a human...
人間ノクセニ
くっ こんな所で
Here of all places?!
あれが... ？
What's that?
It's dangerous, run away.
（九太） 危険だ 逃げて
What are you doing?!
何してる
Go quickly!
行け 早く ！
No!
I won't let go!
離さないから
キュッ
Damn!
くそっ ！
（女） キャッ
Run as fast as you can!
全力で走って
Stay away!
離れてて ！
What's going on?
（女） 何 何？
（男） ＴＶの撮影か何かか？
Are they filming a movie?
ぐわっ
Ren-kun!
蓮くん ！
（九太） くそっ ここじゃダメだ
Damn, we can't fight here.
I need to find a better place.
どこか場所は？
Whale...?
クジラ... ？
It's dangerous, don't go that way!
危険だ ！
そっちに行っちゃダメだ ！
Run away quickly!
早く逃げろ ！
What's this?
何これ
（男） 何の影？
A shadow?
What's that?
（男） あれは？
A whale...?
（女） クジ... ラ... ？
Get out of your cars! Just do it!
車から降りろ
いいから ！
（ドライバー） わああっ
Huh, what?!
何だ？ おい 逃げろ
Run away! Run away quickly!
早く逃げろ ！
Run!
（九太） 走れ ！
Kaede!
楓 ！
How can I defeat him...?
どうやって あいつを倒す？
This way!
こっち ！
Where are we going?!
（九太） どこ行くんだ
How should I handle this?
（九太の声） あいつに対抗するには
どうすればいい？
If I open up my empty heart,
俺のからっぽの胸の仲を
開けて
あいつの闇全部を
閉じ込めたら
lock up all his darkness in there,
and stab myself, will it disappear with me?
自分に剣を突き立てて
道連れに この世から
消えてしまうか
もう俺にできることは
それしかないのか
Is that the only option I have left?
（楓） 私ね
You see, I've been thinking about this since before.
さっきからずっと
考えてたんだけど
Why did I grab your hand and run with you?
なんで蓮くんの手を握って
一緒に走ってるんだろうって
I was really scared, so why?
怖くてたまらないのに
なんでだろうって
Then I remembered.
私 思い出したんだ
最初に蓮くんと会って
一緒に勉強を始めた時
Around the time I first met you and we studied together,
I was really happy.
すごく うれしかったってこと
だって こんなに
楽しそうに勉強する人
Because there's no one else who enjoys studying so much!
他にいないんだもの
一緒にいると
Being with you encouraged me to do my best, too.
私もがんばろうって
勇気が出たんだよ
And I still feel the same.
だから今だって同じなんだ
If you're going to fight, I'll come with you.
蓮くんが戦っているなら
私も一緒にいる
Don't forget.
忘れないで
We never fight alone.
私たち いつだって
たった １ 人で戦ってるわけじゃ
ないんだよ
Kaede...
楓...
（車内アナウンス）
お客様にお知らせいたします
To all passengers.
渋谷駅付近で
火災が発生したため
Due to a fire at the Shibuya station,
この電車は当駅で
運転を見合わせ しばらく...
we must ask you to...
What are these tremors?
（議員 １ ） 何だ この震動は？
Ichirouhiko is targeting Kyuuta...
（議員２） 一郞彦が九太を狙って
人の街で暴れているのだ
and running wild in the human city.
（議員３） 我らの世界と互いに
響き合っているとはいえ
Our worlds may be connected,
こんなにも影響があるとは...
but for us to be affected this much...
Why must we be involved in a dispute between humans?
人同士の争いに
なぜ我らが
巻き込まれねばならないのか
It was wrong to drag humans into our world in the first place.
（議員 １ ） そもそも我らの世界に
人を引き入れたのが
間違いなのだ
ほう...
ハァ... ハァ...
Hey Kumatetsu, don't push yourself or you'll die!
おいおい 熊徹
ムチャすんな 死ぬぞ ！
You're in no condition to move around!
まともに動ける状熊じゃ
ないだろ
Shut up!
うるせえ ！
I've heard what's going on.
事情は聞いたぜ
I'll do something about it.
俺が何とかする 俺が...
I will...
Kumatetsu...
熊徹
What can you do?!
お前に何が
できるってんだよ ！
Grandmaster, you're the only one...
（熊徹） 宗師 あんたしかいねえ
The only one who can do something about this.
何とかできんのは あんただ
But you're keeping the method to yourself!
だが あんたはその方法を
腹にしまって出さねえ
Method?
方法だと ？
What method is there?
どんな方法があるのだ
Kyuuta may think he can stand on his own,
九太は自分じゃ
一人前のつもりでいるが
but he still needs someone to look out for him.
今はまだ誰かの助けが
必要なんだ
俺ぁ 半端モンの
バカ野郎だが
I might be a blockhead, but I want to support him.
それでも あいつの役に
立ってやるんだ
What he lacks in his heart, I'll fill up.
あいつの胸ん中の
足りねえもんを
俺が埋めてやるんだ
それが
半端モンの俺にできるーー
That's the one thing even a blockhead like me can do!
たった １ つのことなんだよ ！
If you're saying something like this, that means...
お前がそんなことを
言うようになるとは
こやつはな
He's saying he wants me to hand over my right to reincarnate.
わしの転生する権利を
寄こせと言うとる
He wants to reincarnate as a god?
神様に転生するだと ？
Ridiculous!
バカな そんなことは
普通のバケモノにはできん
That's not something ordinary beasts can do!
それこそ
宗師様にでもならなきゃ...
Only a grandmaster can do it!
Right now...
今は...
熊徹が宗師だ
Kumatetsu is the grandmaster.
Listen well, Kumatetsu.
（宗師） よく聞け 熊徹
Once done, there's no turning back.
一度決めたら
後戻りはできん
Do you still want to?
それでもよいか？
Yeah...
You really are something...
お前という奴は
迷いなど
みじんもない目をしおって...
There's not a glimpse of hesitation in your eyes.
ハァ ハァ ハァ...
一郞彦
Ichirouhiko.
消えた ？
He disappeared?
Damn!
くそっ ！
危ない ！
Look out!
逃げろ 楓
奴は俺を狙ってる
Run away, Kaede.
He's after me.
楓 ！
Kaede!
What is it you want?
（楓） あなたは何がしたいの？
To cut the opponent you detest into pieces?!
憎い相手を
ズタズタに引き裂きたい？
Will you feel satisfaction from crushing him under your feet?!
踏みにじって
力で押さえつけて満足する？
You may have taken that form,
あなたは
そんな姿をしているけど
but you're just a human obsessed with revenge!
報復に取り慿かれた
人間そのものよ ！
Everyone has a some darkness in him!
誰だって みんな等しく
闇を持ってる
Ren-kun does, too!
蓮くんだって抱えてる ！
私だって ！
Me, too!
Even now, I'm struggling against it with all my strength.
私だって抱えたまま
今も一生懸命もがいてる
That's why there's no way Ren-kun would lose to you,
who easily let himself be consumed by his darkness.
だから...
簡単に闇に のみ込まれた
あなたになんか
蓮くんが負けるわけがない
私たちが負けるわけ
ないんだから ！
There's no way we'll lose!
Kaede!
楓 ！
蓮くん ！
Ren-kun!
I have no other choice.
（九太の声） もう仕方ない
Ichirouhiko, look!
一郞彦 見ろ ！
I'll take in all your darkness!
お前の闇を
全部取り込んでやる
キュッ...
キュ キュ...
キュ～ッ ！
キュッ
Ren-kun, could it be...
蓮くん まさか...
Disappear along with me!
俺と一緒に消えてなくなれ ！
Ren-kun!
蓮くん ！
You can't lose!
負けちゃダメ ！
Kyuuta!
（多々良） 九太 ！
What is this?
これは？
Kyuuta, that's Kumatetsu!
（多々良） 九太
そいつは熊徹だ ！
He reincarnated as a tsukumogami...
"god of tool"
九十九神に転生して
その大太刀に姿を変えたのだ
and took on the shape of that sword!
This is... him?
これが... あいつ？
That idiot said he wants to become the sword in your heart!
（多々良） あの野郞
お前の胸の中の剣に
なるんだとよ
The sword in my heart?
胸の中の剣 ？
You have one in your heart, don't you?!
（熊徹） あるだろ 胸ん中の剣が ！
Huh? How could I have such a thing?
（九太） は？ そんなもんあるか
The sword in your heart is important!
胸ん中の剣が重要なんだよ
It's right here!
ここんとこの ！ ここんとこの ！
Right here!
（熊徹） へへっ
見込んだとおりだぜ
I knew you had something in you!
I'm starting to like you!
ますます気に入った ！
All right, from now on, you're Kyuuta!
じゃ おめえは今から
「九太」 だ
All right, Kyuuta!
よし 九太
I'll train you thoroughly, prepare yourself!
しっかり鍛えてやるから
覚悟しとけ ！
Kyuuta!
（熊徹） 九太 ！
What are you crying for, you idiot?
何泣いてんだ バカ野郞
I hate whiny people!
メソメソしてる奴は
嫌いなんだよ ！
Shut up, I'm not crying!
うるせえ
泣いてねえよ ！
Gather your energy!
（熊徹） 気を溜めろ ！
Kyuuta.
九太
Ren-kun.
蓮くん
Not yet!
（熊徹） まだだ もっと鋭く
研ぎ澄ませ ！
Hone it even further!
あれは？
What's that?
Ichirouhiko appears for an instant before every leap.
（九太の声） 跳躍の瞬間
必ず一郎彦が姿を現す
In that case...
ならば...
Choose one point to attack.
（熊徹） ただ １ 点だけを
見極めろ
そこを迷わず狙い討て ！
Aim for it without hesitation!
Now! Go!
今だ 行け ！
Did he finish it?
やった... か？
No.
いいや
（一郎彦の声） 人間ノ
Even though... you're just a human...
ク乜ニ...
一郞彦
Ichirouhiko.
We're the same.
君は俺と同じだよ
We were raised by beasts.
バケモノに育てられた
バケモノの子だ
We're the children of beasts.
Where...
ここは一体...
...am I?
どこだ？
父上 母上
Father, Mother, Jiroumaru.
二郞丸
What was I doing till now...?
僕は今まで何をして...
I remember going to the match with everyone...
確か闘技場に
みんなと行って...
This is Kyuuta's...
これは九太の...
Do you understand, Kyuuta?
（熊徹） いいか 九太
I'm the type that doesn't change his mind once he's decided on something.
俺はこうだといったん決めたら
それ以上 曲げねえ性分だ
フッ わかってるよ
I know.
If you hesitate, I'll kick your ass from inside your heart!
フラフラ迷ってると
胸ん中から ぶっとばすぞ
Shut up, I won't hesitate.
うるせえ 迷わねえよ
That's the way.
そうこなくっちゃな
ヒヒヒ...
You just shut up and watch what I do.
俺のやることを
そこで黙って見てろ
おうっ
見せてもらおうじゃねえか
Show me then.
（アナウンサー） 昨夜 東京渋谷で
無人の大型トレーラーが暴走し
Last night, in Tokyo Shibuya, a driver-less truck caused an accident leading to a big explosion.
大きな爆発が起きました
During the evacuation, several people were injured,
避難する際に転倒するなどして
多数のケガ人が出ましたが
but the injuries were only minor.
いずれも軽傷だということです
According to the police, right before the accident,
警察によりますと事故の直前
many witnesses reported seeing a whale-shaped shadow,
「クジラのような影を見た」
という通報が
数多く寄せられている
ということですが
but the security cameras didn't show anything of the like.
防犯カメラには何も
映っていなかったという...
Take a good look.
（百秋坊） よーく見ろ
Even Kyuuta was once just a weak child.
あの九太も最初は
ただの ひ弱な子供だったんだ
つまりだ
In other words, if you keep up your daily training,
お前たちだって
毎日の修行に精を出せば
you'll one day be able to stand on your own.
そのうちいつかは
一人前になる...
Probably.
かもしれない
かもな
I missed my chance to reincarnate as a god because of Kumatetsu.
神に転生するせっかくの
チャンスを
熊徹のせいで
フイにしてしもうた
I have to go back to being the grandmaster...
また宗師の職に逆戻り じゃ
Now, now.
まあまあ 今日は
九太を祝う宴じゃ
Today we celebrate for Kyuuta.
Cheers!
（賢者たち） じゃあ かんぱー...
（宗師） ん？
What?
Oh, look at that!
おお あれを見よ
That girl is yet another one of those who support Kyuuta.
あの少女もまた
九太を支えた者の １ 人じゃ
Kaede, what are you doing here?
楓 どうしてここに ？
フフッ お呼ばれしちゃった
I've been invited.
Ah, I had dropped this on the street.
あっ これ
途中で落としちゃって
捜すのに苦労したんだ
Finding it was difficult.
Here, I'm returning it.
はい 返す
ありがとう
Thanks.
それとこれ 高認の願書
And there's also the application for the entrance test.
Do you still feel like taking it?
どうする？
まだ受ける気ある？
You have to make the decision yourself.
どうするか
蓮くんが選ぶんだよ
受ける
I'll take it.
Yes!
やったあ ！
That what I thought!
そうだと思ってたんだ
一緒にがんばろう
Let's do our best together!
I'm starting with the fireworks!
（バケモノ２５） 花火上げるぞ ！
よう
Hey!
（百秋坊） それから九太は
渋天街を出て
After that, Kyuuta left Juutengai and never held a sword again.
二度と剣を持つことはなかった
But there's no better swordsman.
（多々良） だが誰よりも強え剣士だ
（百秋坊） ああ 胸の中に
熊徹という剣を持つ
Yeah, he has a sword named Kumatetsu in his heart.
He's a unique swordsman.
唯一の剣士だ
No matter how hard it may become for him from now on,
（多々良） あいつなら
これから どれだけ
しんどいことがあったって
he'll definitely get through it.
必ず成し遂げるだろうよ
Aren't you glad, Ren?
（九太の母の声）
よかったね 蓮
Bakemono no Ko
hidai shita monsuta no atama wo kakushimotta sandanjuu de shitomeru
I shoot the head of the fat monster with my concealed shotgun
¶ 肥大した
モンスターの頭を
¶ 隠し持った散弾銃で
仕留める
kondo koso chuucho nado sezu ni
this time, without hesitation,
¶ 今度こそ
躊躇などせずに
sono hikigane wo hikitai
I want to pull the trigger
¶ その引き金を引きたい
aitsu no shoutai ha kyoeishin
Is he actually vain?
¶ あいつの正体は
虚栄心？
shippai wo osoreru kyoufushin
Does he fear mistakes?
¶ 失敗を恐れる恐怖心？
mochiagerare ukiashidatte fukureagatta jisonshin
Or does his conceits swell up with flattery?
¶ 持ち上げられ
浮き足立って
¶ 膨れ上がった自尊心？
saa midareta kokyuu wo totonoe
Calming down my shaken breathing
¶ さぁ 乱れた呼吸を整え
¶ 指先に
意識を集めていく
yubisaki ni ishiki wo atsumeteiku
I gather my consciousness in my fingertip
boku dake ga ikeru sekai de juusei ga todoroku
A gunshot roars in the world only I can go to
¶ 僕だけが行ける世界で
銃声が轟く
mabayui hakanai senkou ga kaketeitta
A dazzling, fleeting flash of light sprung forth
¶ 眩い 儚い 閃光が
駆けていった
nanika ga owari mata nanika ga hajimarunda
"Something ends and something begins"
¶ 「何かが終わり また
何かが始まるんだ」
¶ そう きっとその光は
僕にそう叫んでる
sou kitto sono hikari ha boku ni sousakenderu
I'm sure that's what the light cries at me
oitsumeta monsuta no me no okuni
Deep within the cornered monster's eyes
¶ 追い詰めた
モンスターの目の奥に
kodoku to junsuisa wo mitsukeru
I find loneliness and innocence
¶ 孤独と純粋さを見付ける
suterareta koneko mitai ni
like an abandoned kitten
¶ 捨てられた子猫みたいに
karada wo marume obieteru
he curls up, frightened
¶ 身体を丸め怯えてる
aa kono mama ropude tsunaide kainarashiteku koto ga dekitanara
If I can put a rope on him and domesticate him like this
¶ あぁ このまま
ロープで繫いで
¶ 飼い慣らしてくことが
出来たなら
ikutsu mono sentakushi to kanousei ni kakomare
I'm surrounded by countless choices and possibilities
¶ いくつもの選択肢と
可能性に囲まれ
sagashite nozondeta mono ga boyaketeiku
What I was looking for and wishing for becomes blurred
¶ 探してた 望んでた
ものがぼやけていく
nanika ga umare mata nanika ga shindeikunda
"Something is born and something dies"
¶ 「何かが生まれ また
何かが死んでいくんだ」
¶ そう きっとそこからは
逃げられはしないだろう
sou kitto soko kara ha nigerare ha shinai darou
I'm sure he won't run away from there
odayaka sugiru yuugure
The gently passing evening
¶ 穏やか過ぎる夕暮れ
mayonaka no shijima
The silence of the dead of night
¶ 真夜中の静寂
mata monsuta ga abaredasu
The monsters get enraged once again
¶ またモンスターが暴れだす
boku ha sotto iki wo koroshi
I hold my breath quietly
¶ 僕はそうっと息を殺し
¶ 弾倉に弾を込める
dansou ni tama wo komeru
And load bullets into the magazine
kono shizuka na sakki wo kanzukarechi mawanu youni
getting a smell of this quiet bloodlust
¶ この静かな殺気を
¶ 感づかれちまわぬように
kyou mo boku dake ga ikeru sekai de juusei ga todoruku
Today again a gunshot roars in the world only I can go to
¶ 今日も
僕だけが行ける世界で
¶ 銃声が轟く
mabayui hakanai senkou ga kaketeitta
A dazzling, fleeting flash of light sprung forth
¶ 眩い 儚い 閃光が
駆けていった
nanika ga owari mata nanika ga hajimarunda
"Something ends and something begins"
¶ 「何かが終わり また
何かが始まるんだ」
¶ こうしてずっと
この世界は廻ってる
koushite zutto kono sekai ha mawatteru
This is how this world will always go round
nanika ga owari mata nanika ga hajimarunda
"Something ends and something begins"
¶ 「何かが終わり また
何かが始まるんだ」
kitto kitto
Definitely, definitely
¶ きっと きっと